<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A returne from Argier A sermon preached at Minhead in the county of Somerset the 16. of March, 1627. at the re-admission of a relapsed Christian into our Church. By Edward Kellet Doctor of Diuinity.</title>
            <author>Kellett, Edward, 1583-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04776</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108040</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843730</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843730</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8483</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04776)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8483)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 760:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A returne from Argier A sermon preached at Minhead in the county of Somerset the 16. of March, 1627. at the re-admission of a relapsed Christian into our Church. By Edward Kellet Doctor of Diuinity.</title>
                  <author>Kellett, Edward, 1583-1641.</author>
                  <author>Byam, Henry, 1580-1669. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 78, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] H[arper] for I[ohn] P[arker] and are to be sold by Richard Thrale, dwelling in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Crosse-Keyes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>"A returne from Argier .. by Henry Byam" has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8483:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8483:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A RETVRNE FROM ARGIER.</p>
                  <p>A Sermon Preached at <hi>Minhead</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet</hi> the 16. of <hi>March,</hi> 1627. at the re-admiſſion of a relapſed Chriſtian into our CHVRCH.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Edward Kellet</hi> Doctor of Diuinity.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>IEREM. 3.22.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Returne ye back-ſliding Children, and I will heale your backe-ſlidings: behold we come vnto thee, for thou art the Lord our God.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. H.</hi> for <hi>I. P.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Thrale,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the Croſſe-Keyes, 1628.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8483:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8483:2"/>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Countryman of ours goinge from the Port of <hi>Mynhead</hi> in <hi>Sommerſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> bound for the ſtreights, was taken by <hi>Turkiſh Pyrats,</hi> and made a ſlaue at <hi>Argier,</hi> and liuing there in ſlauerie, by frailty and weakeneſſe, for ſooke the Chriſtian Religion, and turned <hi>Turke,</hi> and liued ſo ſome yeares; and in that time ſeruing in a <hi>Turkiſh Ship,</hi> which was taken by an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> of warre, was brought backe againe to <hi>Mynhead,</hi> where being made to vnderſtand the grieuouſneſſe of his Apoſtacy, was very penitent for the ſame, &amp; deſired to be reconciled to the Church, vnto which he was admitted by the authority of the Lord Biſhop of that Dioces, with aduiſe of ſome great and learned Prelates of this Kingdome, and was enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned pennance for his Apoſtacy: and at his admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and performance thereof, theſe two Sermons were Preached, the third Sunday in Lent. <hi>Anno 1627.</hi> one in the Forenoone, the other in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8483:3"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8483:3"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>GALATIANS 5.2.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Jf yee be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe giddie times, when it is eſteemed a piece of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for the People to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their Prieſts; if I bee blamed, and it bee iudged vnfit,
<note n="a" place="margin">Front eſt oci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitio prior, &amp; ſedulus paſtor, ſuis magis ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, quàm alienit greges ſuos quàm alienos luſtrare debet. Dictum Xauerij.</note> that I ſpend my paines this Sabbath, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans Cure, and not in my owne; let mee aſſume this iuſt defence, That I was neuer abſent
<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Non licentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſâ libertate, ſed neceſſariâ ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute;</hi> which was S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> his excuſe to the Clergie, and people of <hi>Hippo, Epiſt.</hi> 138.</note> wilfully; and though I might alleadge, that euery true Paſtor, is a Paſtor in any part of the world; and we are commanded, when we haue opportunity, to doe good, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. and there is no ſuch opportunity of doing good, as when expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is raiſed, by new or ſtrange occurrences: yea, we are bound, not onely to doe good, but to doe the moſt good we can;
<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 17.10.</note> and if wee could doe all that is commanded, we haue done but what was our dutie to doe. Yet more fully to free, both my moſt worthy fellow-labourer, and my ſelfe, from the aſperſion of intruſion, and of being Polypragmons (which hath beene whiſpered among you) be pleaſed to know, that no part of this buſineſſe, is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8483:4"/>vndertaken of our owne heads, but all by the direction of our lawfull Superiours. And if it were but a thing in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, wee might not diſobey them;
<note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>In adiaphoris. licèt per ſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncti operis qualitas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxia ſit, adiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lae tamen au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatis pondus, obnoxium man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dato; manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumque, peccato facit obnoxium,</hi> Bernard.</note> but being ſo good in it ſelfe, and vpon ſo vnuſuall an accident, when a great doore, and effectuall, is opened vnto vs,
<note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.9. <hi>Oſtium pro Occaſione,</hi> Act. 14.27, <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi>
                     </note> if wee deſerue no thankes, yet we feare no reproofe, vnleſſe this be imputed for one; That I am ſo long from my Text.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>If yee be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>THat the Apoſtle ſpake to the Galatians, euery one knoweth; but, neither what the Galatians were, is ſo manifeſt vnto all, nor why hee wrote thus vnto the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians. Firſt, of the firſt. The Galatians were not people of one Citie, as the Romans and Corinthians, and the like were; nor was any Citie of the world called <hi>Galatia,</hi> but it is the name of a whole country, ſituated in <hi>Leſſer-Aſia,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led firſt <hi>Gallo-Graecia,</hi> becauſe of the French Colonies thither tranſplanted, and there fixed, and then <hi>Galatia:</hi> which contained a great tract of ground, (as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by its
<note n="f" place="margin">Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ad Orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m ſpectat, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padociae &amp; Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-fluui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> finiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a, ab Occidente, sythiniâ, à Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>idie, Pamphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liâ; à Septentri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, Ponto Eux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o slauditur.</note> boundaries) in which were three famous Cities, (ſaith <hi>Pliny</hi>) and innumerable Churches;
<note n="g" place="margin">
                        <hi>In quâ Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias erant innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>erabiles,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in his Booke d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vnitate Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> all which were planted, and watered by the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who reduced them from idolatrie and Paganiſme, vnto Chriſtianity; <hi>For he went ouer all the Country of Galatia, in order, ſtrengthening all the Diſciples,</hi> Acts 18.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillatim, one Church after another;</hi> euery Church hee viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
<note n="h" place="margin">Muſculus in Praeſat. in Epiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Galat.</note> Now as this is the onely Epiſtle of his thirteene, which was written to a whole Prouince, to all the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of Galatia; and a large letter written with his owne hand, which he did not doe often, and therefore intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that they ſhould conſider of it, as a ſingular teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his loue; <hi>You ſee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>how large a letter I haue written to you with mine owne hand, Gal.</hi> 6.11. ſo the cauſe why he wrote it, was remarkable, and is now to be vnfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
                  <p>After that the good ſeede of the Goſpell was ſowed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8483:4"/>amongſt them, whilſt S. <hi>Paul</hi> (whoſe iuriſdiction was not limited) did labour other-where, in the conuerſion of others, there were certaine halfe-fac'd Chriſtians, who receiued Chriſt, as a Preacher of the Truth, as a patterne of Holineſſe in his owne perſon, as a guide vnto perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for all them that beleeued in him. But the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes, and Reconciliation with God, and the iuſtification of Man, they aſcribed to the workes of the Law, and not to Chriſt. Briefly, to our purpoſe, thus, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1. <hi>Certaine men came downe from Iudea, and taught the Brethren,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Except yee be circumciſed after the manner of</hi> Moſes, <hi>yee cannot be ſaued:</hi> what ſort of men, theſe Seducers were, is mentioned, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.5. <hi>They were of the ſect of the Phariſees, which beleeued.</hi> Theſe Chriſtian-Iewes, or Iewiſh-Chriſtians, would ioyne <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> forgetting the ſubſtance of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts giuen vnto them, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt not let thy Cattle gender with a diuers kinde; Thou ſhalt not ſow thy field with a mingled ſeed, neither ſhall a garment of linnen and wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len come vpon thee.</hi> And <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.9. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſow thy vineyard with diuers ſeeds, nor plough with an Oxe and an Aſſe together.</hi> Nor would they remember what was written in the Goſpell, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.16. <hi>No man putteth a piece of new cloth vpon an old garment; neither doe men put new wine into olde bottles.</hi> All which places, doe in their morall, forbid mingling of Religions, as the Fathers expound them:
<note n="i" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nefas eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> veteribus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcere,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> and he proueth it from the place of S. <hi>Math. Tertullian</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth by them, the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, <hi>In lib. de Oratione, cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Chriſtus nouis Diſcipulis, nouam orationis formam deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minauit. Oporte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat enim, in hac quo<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſpecie, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum vinum, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis vtribus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condi; &amp; nou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> plagulam, nous aſſui veſtimento.</hi> See him to the ſame effect, <hi>contra Marcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> 3.15. <hi>&amp; contra eundem,</hi> 4.11. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the former place of <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> though I will not ſay with <hi>Caietan</hi> it is not to be vnderſtood literally; becauſe they had many Mules at one time, euen 245. <hi>Ezra</hi> 2.66. &amp; others ordinarily, at other times, before that, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.29. yet I will ſay with <hi>Iſychius,</hi> The mingling of the Iewiſh and Chriſtian Religion, might be aymed at; that the water of Baptiſme, was to waſh away the bloud of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, that the Oblation on the Altar of the Croſſe, being at the time of the Euening Sacrifice, was to conſummate all Sacrifices. <hi>Procopius Gazaeus,</hi> on the place. <hi>Non abſurde, praedictis ſub inuolucris, prohibet, ne diuerſam ſectemur Religionem.</hi> And for the place of the Oxe and the Aſſe in <hi>Deuter. Procopius</hi> ſaith well; <hi>Bos, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictimae, Cibó<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſacer eſt: cùm Aſinus neutrius vſum praebeat:</hi> and ſince he applieth the Aſſe to Heretikes or Grecians, I thinke I may much more to the Iewiſh Ceremonies, which were as the Aſſe that Chriſt rid vpon; and did carry Chriſt, as the Aſſe did <hi>Iſis,</hi> when as he ſaid truely, <hi>Non tibi, ſed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioni:</hi> ſo the reſpect was borne to the Ceremonies, not for their own ſake, but for Chriſts.</note> ſo, whilſt they would be both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> they were neither true <hi>Iewes,</hi> nor perfect <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:8483:5"/>
                  <p>Of this kind, were the <hi>Millenaries</hi> long after, who would haue the Law and Circumciſion in force with the Goſpell, whom <hi>Epiphanius Haereſ.</hi> 77, From my Text con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futeth: yet through the inticing of thoſe falſe Brethren, the ſimple <hi>Galatians</hi> were bewitched; and began to place confidence in the vertue of Circumciſion. Our holy Apoſtle in two Epiſtles doth many wayes confute this error. It is an idle diſtinction, which <hi>Cornelius Cornelij à Lapide</hi> the Ieſuit maketh, betweene the Epiſtle to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> and this Epiſtle; That this was written againſt the Gentiles onely, but the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> was writ againſt both Iewes and Gentiles: for, the Apoſtle heere wrote, againſt the Gentiles for <hi>Iudaizing;</hi> and againſt the Iewes for ſeducing them. <hi>Tertullian aduerſùs Marcionem lib.</hi> 5, ſaith, This is the principall Epiſtle, <hi>aduerſùs Iudai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmum.</hi> But an exacter difference is this: In this Epiſtle he fighteth chiefly againſt the Ceremonials, to which the Gentiles were now incaptiuated; In the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> his maine force is bent, againſt the morall works of the Law, of which the Iewes boaſted, aboue the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; that euen they, do not iuſtifie a ſinner, much leſſe the Ceremonials, but onely Faith in Chriſt. Fetch all the Arguments, who pleaſeth, at the fountaines head; this being an eaſie <hi>Epitome</hi> of it: that conuincing by deeper demonſtration, and eloquence maieſticall; this Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> rather reproouing, then teaching, in phraſes not ſo loftie, as homely, and fitting to new conuerts.
<note n="k" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hierom</hi> thus <hi>Altuiri ſenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, &amp; profundiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus vſus eſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentis ad Romanos. Ad Galatas, modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s ſtilo, incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pat potiùs quàm docet, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munes ſententias communi orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> veſtit.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But let vs come, firſt to the wordes in a lumpe; then to the pointes in ſeuerall,</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Syriac</hi> hath it, <hi>If you Be circumciſed, Chriſt doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit you nothing.</hi> May I adde, if it had beene read, <hi>If you ſhall be circumciſed Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing:</hi> that there in no difference, in ſence from theſe words, <hi>If you Be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing.</hi> For, all the three Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, run to this head, to ſhew the praeſent dangerous eſtate of them, who truſt in Circumciſion.</p>
                  <p>The points doe follow.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:8483:5"/>
                  <p n="1">1. From the Perſons ſpoken vnto, viz the <hi>Galatians. If ye be circumciſed,</hi> is afforded libertie to examine, whither the Iewes, and Gentiles, where vnder the ſame tye and yoke, concering <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> when S. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote thus? 2. From the Commination, <hi>Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing,</hi> is occaſion adminiſtred to ſhew, what the loſſe of Chriſt is, and how heinous is that ſinne of beeing circumciſed, which is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſo dread-full a puniſhment, as the receauing of no benefit by the death of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But ſet the Emphaſis on <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and weigh, that he ſaith not, If ye haue bin circumciſed, but, <hi>ſi circumcidamini, If ye be Circumciſed;</hi> then thirdly and laſtly, from the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tenſe of the verbe, as the former point is punctually eſtabliſhed, viz the danger of damnation, that they are in for the praeſent, who truſt in Circumciſion, and are Iewes in heart; ſo is it not auerred nor intended, that a Gentile Circumciſed, and after repenting, is in that woefull caſe: but rather from the preſent danger of obſtinate Iudai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing-Gentils, the future freedome of the Circumciſed Gentile, whenſoeuer hee becommeth a Repentant Chriſtian, may be iuſtly gathered, or inferred. Thus did the preſent occaſion ſet me on this Text, and the pointes are drawne and ſorted to the preſent occaſion. Proceed we now orderly.</p>
                  <p>Whereas the firſt Quaere is, Whither Iewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, were equally bound, to abandon Circumciſion; I diſtinguiſh, that the Iewes were of two ſortes, the firſt, Obſtinate vnbeleeures, who had no part in Chriſt, and of thoſe, the quaeſtion is not vnderſtood: the ſecond ſort, were Iewes, yet Diſciples, party-coloured Chriſtians, and thoſe mens caſe, varied from the Gentiles. For, though it had been their ſafeſt way, to haue renounced <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> after they were initiated into Chriſt, yet theſe men might haue kept vp Circumciſion, which was wholy forbid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Gentiles. Indeed at any time, after Chriſt's death, if the Iewes had vſed Circumciſion, as thinking it abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſarie to ſaluation, they had ſinned
<note n="l" place="margin">
                        <hi>Credeban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc Signum du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare, &amp; tunc ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnatum nondum veniſſe, &amp; ſic excidebant à Chriſto. Aquin.</hi> in his Lection on my Text.</note> For it was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8483:6"/>a type of Chriſt, and in effect, they had denied Chriſt to be the Meſſias, who ſo truſted in Circumciſion: yet in other reſpects, it was, it might be in long vſe after S. <hi>Hierom</hi> did well maintaine, that the Ceremonials were neither <hi>mortna,</hi> nor <hi>mortifera,</hi> till Chriſt's Paſſion, but hee erred in ſaying, that they might not be vſed, without ſinne, after Chriſt's Death.
<note n="m" place="margin">See <hi>Aquin.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 103. <hi>Artic</hi> 4.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> more conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently tripartites the time: firſt, Whil'ſt Chriſt liued (ſaith he) the Ceremonialls were in force: ſecondly, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt's Death, and the Publication of the Goſpell the Ceremonialls were dead, as hauing no vertue in them, &amp; none were bound to keepe them: yet were they not wholy vnlawfull: thirdly, after the Preaching of the Goſpell, they were both dead, and deadly, vnprofitable in themſelues, and ſinnefull to others, in their vſe. Yet euen this laſt Poſition, is not ſound, vnleſſe we ſtretch it, to a large latepatencie
<note n="n" place="margin">
                        <hi>Scotus</hi> diſlikes it; and though <hi>Conrade Koellin,</hi> on <hi>Aquin.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">•</hi>, 2<hi>ae. Quaeſt.</hi> 103, taxeth <hi>Scotus,</hi> that he tooke nor aright, what <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi> vnderſtand, by the <hi>Diuulgation</hi> of the Goſpell; and thereupon diſtinguiſheth, There is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Publication of the Goſpell, <hi>Vna imperfecta, quando per Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolos &amp; alios praedicati erant Articuli fidei,</hi> and the Neceſſitie of the Sacraments of the New-Law, and of the Praecepts of Chriſt. The other is the perfect Promulgation of the Goſpell, where the afore-ſaid thinges were preached, and the ſufficiencie of the New-Law without the Legals, and the inutilitie, yea hurt of the Legals. After this Publication, <hi>Aquin</hi> meaneth, it was not lawfull to obſerue <hi>the Legals as Sacraments;</hi> and <hi>Scotus</hi> oppoſeth not this, ſaith <hi>Koellin:</hi> yet he himſelfe is too blame, firſt, in making an imperfect Preaching of the Apoſtles, which was moſt perfect, though indeed not ſo large, or full. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in miſtaking <hi>Aquinas,</hi> who ſaith not any where, it was lawfull to obſerue the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galls as Sacraments, at any time, betweene Chriſt's Death, and the full promulgation of the Goſpell. For it was at no time lawfull, <hi>aftèr the Death of Chriſt, to vſe them, as Sacraments,</hi> and ſo the heart of his diſtinction is broken, which makes is vnlawfull, to vſe Legals, as Sacraments, after the inlarged Promulgation, which was meerely vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, at the firſt, or breifer Publication:</note> For the faith of the Romans, was ſpoken-of, throughout the whole world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8. And, the Goſpell was in all the world, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.6. And the Apoſtles had in their perfecteſt Counſaile at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> determined againſt the Ceremonials, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.10.—Yet after this, <hi>S. Paul</hi> did Circumciſie <hi>Timothie,</hi> Act. 16.3. <hi>and ſhaued his head at Cenchrea,</hi> Act. 18.18. And the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials might lawfully be practized euen after this, vpon two eſpeciall reaſons: firſt, becauſe they were not <hi>buried,</hi>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:8483:6"/>though they were <hi>dead.</hi> For, if not only Princes, but No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-men, yea very meane perſons ſometimes, after they haue expired, be kept aboue ground, that they may bee more honorably, and ſolemnly interred, then why not <hi>Moſes?</hi> Why not his Law, which being ſo full of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, was not to want that ordinarie, great and laſt Ceremonie of a prolonged, ſtately, Princely, buriall? If any one be ſo curious, as to ſearch, What day, what howre the Funeralls were ended, and exactly, when it was firſt a ſinne, for the Iewiſh-Chriſtians, to bee Circumciſied? I will anſwer, that as the Lord buried <hi>Moſes, and no man knoweth of his Sepulcher, vnto this day, Deuter.</hi> 34.6. ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it was a prognoſtick, that no man ſhould know that Article of time, when the Ceremonies were ſo accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhedly interred, that the vſe of them, ſhould begin to be ſinnefull.
<note n="o" place="margin">
                        <hi>Quando iſta publicatio facta ſit, non Legitur in Scripturâ,</hi> ſaith <hi>Koellin ibid.</hi> and he ſpeaketh of the extended, and (as hee calleth it) the perfeſt promulgation of the Goſpell.</note> yet this ſhall not hinder me from ſhewing my gueſſe, and priuate opinion, That the Moſaicall Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies were buried in the ruines of the Temple, or rather in the diſperſion, vnder <hi>Adrian,</hi> as will probably ariſe from the next reaſon. The ſecond reaſon, why after Chriſt's death, yea, after the manifeſtation of the Goſpell, the Ceremonialls were not quite aboliſhed, but permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is drawne from the ſcandall of the weake Brethren, in whoſe behalfe, and for whoſe ſaluation, theſe things were lawfully put in vre, which otherwiſe had beene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull. For, though we neede not yeeld any thing, when there is an obdurate paſſiue
<note n="p" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Booke <hi>de Velandis wir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginibus, Bonae res neminem ſcandalizant ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi malam men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Si bonum eſt modeſtia, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recundia, faſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium gloriae, agnoſcant ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſuum, qui de tali bono ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizantur. Quid enim ſi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continentes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant ſe à conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentibus ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizari continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia reuocandane eſt?</hi> S. Hierom <hi>ad Heliodorum</hi> is more loftie and reſolute. <hi>Licèt in limine eaieat pater, per calcatum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem perge, &amp; fixis oculis ad vexillum Crucis euola.</hi>
                     </note> ſcandall; called <hi>Scandalum Iudaeorum,</hi> or <hi>Phariſaeorum,</hi> becauſe, they were offended with Chriſt's wholſome Doctrine, <hi>Matt.</hi> 15.12. <hi>and with the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous rayſing of Lazarus,</hi> Iohn 11.47. <hi>and at his wiſdome and mighty workes,</hi> Matt. 13.57. but we are to follow Chriſt, who did not many mighty workes there, Matt. 13.58. <hi>and went thence,</hi> Ioh. 11.54. and only of them, <hi>Sinite illos, caeci duces ſunt caecorum.</hi> Matt. 15.14. <hi>and yet continued doing of good otherwhere,</hi> Mark. 6.6.
<note n="q" place="margin">Conſider theſe places; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2. <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12—1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19.—1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9—</note> The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 57.14. ſaith, <hi>Not only, lay no ſtumbling block; but if others lay it,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8483:7"/>Take vp the ſtumbling-blocke; not to let it fall againe; but take it out of the way of my people.</hi> And 1. <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Abſtaine from all appearance of ſinne:</hi> that is, though thou ſinneſt not, yet auoyd ſcandall, ſince there needed no abſtaining, from the appearance of euill, if none would take offence at it. In this caſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I would eat no fleſh, while the world ſtandeth, leaſt I make my brother to offend.</hi> Yea, if the feeble Diſciples, be offended, with our omiſſion of things indifferent, we are, no longer, to omit them. Many thouſand Iewes, were turned Chriſtians, who were zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for <hi>Moſes</hi> his Law, <hi>Act.</hi> 21.20. who were ſcandalized by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> as if he had taught all the Iewes, among the Gentiles, to forſake <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying, <hi>that they ought not to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe their children.</hi> S. <hi>Iames</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and his Preſbiters, perſwaded S. <hi>Paul,</hi> to remooue this ſcandall, and to purifie himſelfe, with others, after the manner of the Iewes: yet were the Ceremonials, now, dead, and S. <hi>Paul</hi> had truly preach't againſt them. For all this becauſe this doctrine, was ſcandalous at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> where were more Iewes, then in any City of the world, S. <hi>Paul</hi> did purifie himſelfe: And for the ſame reſpect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Iewes, which were in thoſe quarters, did Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe <hi>Timothy, Act.</hi> 16.3. For, <hi>Timothy</hi> his father being a Greeke, and his mother a Ieweſſe, <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> or <hi>Vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,</hi> was Indifferent: but to eſtabliſh the weake, and remooue ſcandall, did the great Impugner of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> rites, not omit that indifferent Circumciſion. Yea, to take away this ſtone of offence, Circumciſion was retained, a long time, in the Citie of <hi>Hieruſalem, and fifteene Chriſtian Biſhops of Hieruſalem were all ſucceſſiuely of the Circumciſion.</hi> And the firſt Chriſtian Biſhop of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> that was a Gentile, was one <hi>Marcus,</hi> in the Reigne of <hi>Adrian,</hi> after the ouerthrow, both of the Temple, and of the Citie whoſe name <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> was changed into <hi>Aelia.</hi> So ſaith <hi>Nicephorus</hi> 3.25. and <hi>Sulpitius Seuerus lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Hiſtor.</hi> though <hi>Baronius</hi> doth nibble at it, <hi>ad Annum Chriſti</hi> 138. In theſe two caſes onely, <hi>Circumciſion</hi> might without offence, be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8483:7"/>kept on foote, by the beleeuing Iewes, euen after the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation of the Goſpell: though they may praetend a third reaſon, for the continuation of it, from the words of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.13. <hi>My Couenant ſhal bein your fleſh for an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting conenant;</hi> yet they are to know, that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Olano,</hi> importeth not, an abſolute, but a reſpectiue euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: as a Ward, is for euer a Ward, vntill the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of the father, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.2. which euerlaſtingneſſe is not vnlimited, but bounded; not ſimple, but referentiall: ſo circumciſion being but a Type, was to laſt only, to a Typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, paedagogicall, periodicall, euerlaſtingneſſe, that is till the ſubſtance ſhould come. <hi>Deuter.</hi> 15.17. <hi>He ſhal be thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant for euer;</hi> yet in the Chambers of Death, the ſeruant is free from his maſter, <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.19. and nor maſter, nor ſeruant, can liue for euer. <hi>Aeternum ſumitur pro ſaeculo, quod habet fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ſed non determinatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nobis,</hi> ſaith <hi>aquinas.</hi> Thus much be ſpoken, concerning the Iewiſh Chriſtians, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, why Circumciſion was allowed vnto them. Now concerning the Chriſtian-Gentile, hee was not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in any caſe to be Circumciſed, no, though hee were at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> among the fauourers of Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as appeareth by the example of <hi>Titus, Gal.</hi> 2.3. The Apoſtles in their Councell, reckon among other things, Circumciſion, as a trouble to the Gentiles, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.19. and in their miſſiues, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.28. they account it <hi>a burden.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it <hi>an entanglement, a yoke, a bondage,</hi> in the verſe immediatly before my Text; <hi>And I teſtifie againe, vnto euery man, that is circumciſed, that hee is debtor, to doe the whole Law;</hi> immediately after my Text: a poore debtor, wrap't in Bands, worſe then the Bonds of Vſurers; in Bonds forfeited, and impoſſible to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; for no meere man euer kept the whole Law. Now, leaſt that preſumptious credulitie might coſen it ſelfe, in hoping that Chriſt, would be their Mediator, that he had ſatisfied the whole Law for them, and would pay their debt and <hi>blot out the Hand-writing of Ordinances, which was againſt them, and contrarie vnto them, and take it out of the way,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8483:8"/>and nayle it vnto his Croſſe. S. Paul,</hi> with more then common earneſtneſſe, and holy feruencie, proteſteth, <hi>Behold, I</hi> Paul <hi>ſay vnto you, that if you, you</hi> Galatians, <hi>bee Circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">And yet on the other ſide, if a circumciſed Gentile, had after, turned Chriſtian, it is the Apoſtolical rule to his <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.18. Is any man called be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? let him not become vncircumciſed; as it is modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rendered, in our late Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation <hi>Non adducat praepu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> ſaith the Vulgar: but its in the Originall, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>non attrahatur praeputium.</hi> Where the Apoſtle ſecretly reprehendeth, the wicked cuſtome of the Iewes, who by Inſtruments and Medicines made Circumciſion to become vncircumciſion: as appeareth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the oppoſition of the two Verbes, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>; for, they re-skin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſecret part. Hence <hi>Martiall</hi> made mention, <hi>Recutitornm Iudaeorum;</hi> and their very Sabbaoths, eſcaped not the venom of tongues, but were called, <hi>recutita Sabbata.</hi> Though <hi>Origen</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> denyeth ſuch a reduction or dilatation can be, yet <hi>Celſus</hi> that learned Phyſitian 7<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.25. ſaith, it may be. <hi>Theodoret</hi> agreeth with vs. <hi>Epiphanius de Menſurâ &amp; Ponderibus.</hi> about the middeſt of the Booke ſheweth the meanes, and tearmeth the attractorie Inſtrument <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Spaſtherem,</hi> and ſaith, the Iewes doe father the invention of it, on the Renegado <hi>Eſau,</hi> (who ſold away his Birth-right, and thought to fruſtrat the ſigne of the true Religion, perhaps then, when to the griefe of his Parents, hee tooke two wiues, of the <hi>Hittites, Geneſ.</hi> 26.34) — <hi>Certaine it is that they who turned from the Iewiſh Religion, to the Samaritan, or from the Samaritan to the Jewiſh, were twice Circumciſed;</hi> and <hi>Symachus,</hi> who tranſlated the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> into <hi>Graeke,</hi> was twice Circumciſed; ſaith <hi>Epiphanius.</hi> Or if the Iewes embraced the Gentile Religion, as <hi>Menelaus</hi> and <hi>Tobias</hi> his ſonnes did (ſaith <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus Antiquit. Judaic.</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.6<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.) <hi>Adduxerunt ſibi praeputia, vt nudi quo<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> non eſſent Graecis diſſimiles;</hi> which <hi>Ioſephus</hi> horrowed from 1. <hi>Maccab.</hi> 1.17. They made themſelues vncircumciſed; or as the Vulgar hath it, <hi>fecerunt ſibi praeputia.</hi> The Apoſtell, wholy diſliketh the courſe, and would not haue bodily Circumciſion, to bee made Vncircumciſion, when once it is done, yet moſt ſeuerely interdicteth Circumciſion to the Gentile <hi>Galatians. Jf yee be Circumciſed, Chriſt profiteth you nothing.</hi>
                     </note> Thus am I fallen off from the firſt generall part of my Text, which was extracted from the qualitie and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe, to whom our holy Apoſtle wrote; namely, the Galatians, Gentile-Chriſtians, to the ſecond maine point from the Commination it ſelfe; What it is to looſe Chriſt, and the greatneſſe of that ſinne, which is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with the loſſe of ſo great a benefit.</p>
                  <p>The loſſe which one may haue, by the loſſe of Chriſt, can neuer be ſufficiently conceiued, vnleſſe we value the great good and benefit, which we gaine by him.</p>
                  <p>And this good or profit, muſt needes be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derualued, vnleſſe the miſerable eſtate in which we were, before hee helped vs, be conſidered.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:8483:8"/>
                  <p>View therefore:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, our lamentable condition in the ſtate of Nature. Secondly, the infinite bleſſings of our Redemption by the merits of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the loſſe of ſo precious a Iewell, of ſo great riches, as the not being profitable by Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But, firſt, let me haue a venue with the words <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>niſi circumcidamini; Yee cannot be ſaned</hi> ſay the falſe Brethren, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>ſi circumcidamini,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle in my Text, <hi>If ye be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing.</hi> Where S. <hi>Paul</hi> oppoſeth Chriſts not profiting vs, vnto Saluation denyed by the <hi>Pſeudapoſtols;</hi> intimating that Chriſts helpe, affordeth vs ſaluation: Chriſts not profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs, leaues vs in the ſtate of Damnation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, though the word doth more properly, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, betoken gaine, benefit, emolument, or increaſe, as <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> its primitiue, ſignifieth to heape vp, to amaſſe, or gather together: yet by a metaphor, it is deriued, to any manner of helpe, aide, comfort, beneuolence, profit, or aſſiſtance: all which in euery kinde, as the ſound Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian reapeth by his Sauiour, ſo hee who circumciſeth himſelfe, in confidence of its vertue, ſhall gather no fruit by Chriſt, no bleſſing any way. Chriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ſhall profit him nothing.</hi> The circumciſed Chriſtian, <hi>aufert do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicae Paſſionis effectum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquinas</hi> on the place; that is, he is in no better condition, than if Chriſt had not dyed for him; and that eſtate is moſt commiſerable, which is the firſt point to be explained.</p>
                  <p>That we were once happie in <hi>Adam, and might ſo haue continued;</hi> coſteth ſighes to remember, and teares to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: for he repreſented our perſons, and ſtood for Vs <hi>Idealiter,</hi> from which happineſſe he fell, and Wee with Him, and in Him. One ſinne, one ſinne onely, the firſt ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> brought Vs to the Vallie of death, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this wofull plight, (as may be ſeene in my <hi>Miſcellanies,</hi> as yet vnpubliſhed.)</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:8483:9"/>
                  <p>Rich We were, He hath made Vs Poore; yea, by cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Vs, hath made Vs naked. Wee were Lords of the Creatures; now Wee are ſeruants to ſinne. We were in Him the Sonnes of God, <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.38. now we are by Him, the children of wrath, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.3. The obiect of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding was truth; the perfection was knowledge: but now we are ignorant, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18. The obiect of our will was goodneſſe, the perfection Loue but now we are naturally vaine, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.17. The obiect of our iraſcible part, was Difficultie, if any thing then might be ſaid to be difficult, which might haue beene perfected in victorie; but now this facultie is growne infirme: the fleſh luſteth, and as naturall men, we are ſure to be vanquiſhed. The obiect of our part concupiſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le, was moderate delight, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection was contentment; but now we are fallen point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blanke to the contrary, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Omnes morimur in Adamo,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. and through Him, the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of euery one of mankinde, (Chriſt onely excepted, <hi>who is the immaculate Lamb of God</hi>) is corrupted, <hi>ſecundùm ſe totum, &amp; totum ſui:</hi> inſomuch, that all the faculties of our ſoules and bodies are depraued: and euery one is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſubiect to euery ſinne, which hath beene, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after may be committed. He who deſireth to ſee our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature more liuely painted forth, let him haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. from the ninth, to the nineteenth verſe: and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1.2. and 3. verſes, and eſpecially <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>that euery imagination of the thoughts of mans heart, was onely euill continually.</hi> In this deplorable condition, the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> left vs; then commeth the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> our onely Lord and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> (which is the ſecond point, and now to be inſiſted vpon,) <hi>He taketh our nature vpon him, Heb.</hi> 2.16. He vanquiſheth Satan, and his temptations, becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> was vanquiſhed. Hee faſted, becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned by eating: He watcht, He prayed, He fulfilled all the Law: He was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, Hee was bruiſed for our iniquities: the chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our peace, was vpon Him, <hi>and with his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8483:9"/>ſtripes we are healed,</hi> Eſa. 53.5. <hi>God hath made Him to be ſin for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, who kne no ſinne,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.21. <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s from the curſo of the Law, being made accurſed for vs,</hi> Gal. 3.13. For Vs did he ſweat drops of bloud in the Garden; for vs, was Hee nayled to the Croſſe, and put to a moſt ſhamefull death: for vs, did He tread out the Wine-preſſe of Gods wrath alone; and for vs, <hi>appreciatiuè,</hi> ſatisfied the rigour of Gods iuſtice: <hi>He dyed for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our iuſtification,</hi> Rom 425. And now He ſitteth at the right hand of God, ſpeaking better things for vs, than the bloud of <hi>Abel.</hi> And whereas the Accuſer of the Brethren, night and day, ſoliciteth God for vengeance againſt our ſinnes; Chriſt the great Mediator ſtandeth between Gods wrath and vs, and interpoſeth his Merits, giuing vs time to repent.
<note n="ſ" place="margin">There is not a ſentence exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted now, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any of mankinde, but it proceedeth our of the mouth of Chriſt. Indeed <hi>Baſil</hi> againſt <hi>Eunomius</hi> ſaith. <hi>that the Father appeared,</hi> Eſa. 6.1. but it is attributed to Chriſt, <hi>Ioh</hi> 12.40. &amp; 41. and S <hi>Paul</hi> aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth it to the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.25. So that each perſon is Iudge equally, <hi>in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinis:</hi> yet Chriſt hath now this power of <hi>Iudicature,</hi> deputed vnto him. Ioh 5.22. Math. 11 27. Math. 28 18. <hi>He hath the keyes of hell, and of death, Reuel.</hi> 1.18 The Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity iudgeth <hi>authoritatiuè,</hi> Chriſt, <hi>executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uè:</hi> God, by a primarie inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent right; Chriſt, by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legated power: <hi>Eſt in Patre au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas in Filio ſub-authoritas:</hi> Chriſt is not Iudge exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely, or by way of oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or the Spirit; but by appropriation. And this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority he hath as he is Man, Ioh. 5.27. Acts 17.31. And it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him at his Incarnation, Heb. 1.6. But the full actuall admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of this power, was not till his Aſcenſion and ſitting at the right hand of. God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.22 <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Auguſtine de fide &amp; ſymbolo cap.</hi> 7. maketh <hi>ſede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> to ſignifie a <hi>Iudiciarie</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. All this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is proued at full, in my Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellanies of the particular iudgement of ſoules imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately vpon death; which point hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bin hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as it ought or may be.</note> Thus, <hi>are we deliuered from the power of darkeneſſe,</hi> Coloſ. 1.13. yea, <hi>he hath now reconciled vs, who were alienated and enemies,</hi> verſe 21. <hi>We were wounded, and the good Samaritane hath healed vs; We were dead in our ſins, and He hath quickned vs, and hath forgiuen vs all our treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> Col. 2.13. <hi>He is our peace,</hi> Epheſ. 2.14. <hi>In him wee are compleat; In him we are circumciſed, with the Circumciſion made without hands; buried with him, riſen with him,</hi> Coloſ. 2.10. <hi>And God hath made vs ſit together in heauenly places, in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> Epheſ. 2.6. <hi>Chriſt Ieſus of God, is made vnto vs, Wiſedome, and Righteouſneſſe, Sanctification and Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.30. And, <hi>we are made the Righteouſneſſe of God, in Chriſt. We are iuſtified by his bloud, and we ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from wrath by him, Rom.</hi> 5.9. Briefly thus, he hath now done vs more good, than euer <hi>Adam</hi> did harm, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15.</p>
                  <p>For, firſt, <hi>Adam</hi> conueyed vnto vs originall ſinne onely, which cannot be intended, but is alike in all. Chriſt giueth many different graces, and increaſeth them; yea, many, which <hi>Adam</hi> and his poſterity ſhould neuer haue had, if he had not falne: as Patience, Virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Repentance, Bowels of Pitie, and tender commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, fraternall Correction, and the perfection of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, glorious Martyrdome.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8483:10"/>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne, was the ſinne onely of a meere man; Chriſts obedience was the obedience of the Sonne of God, the Mediator betweene God and Man, the Man <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.5. <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne was but the producer of that effect, which muſt needs haue beene in God: for God is neceſſarily iuſt, and could not be otherwiſe. But Chriſt hath brought forth mercy in God, and God might haue beene both God, and a good God, and yet not mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull. For Mercy preſuppoſeth Miſery; <hi>Miſerecordiae propria ſedes eſt, Miſeria,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard;</hi> and Miſery might not haue beene.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, by <hi>Adams</hi> offence, Man is compared to the Beaſts that periſh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.12. By the grace of Chriſt, we ſhall be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>equall to Angels, Mark.</hi> 12.25. Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the beſt, in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> our nature was inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to the Angels, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.7. yea, Chriſt himſelfe on earth, by his ſuffering of death, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. though now we ſee him crowned with glory and honour; yet in other regards, Chriſt is preferred before the Angels, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2.3.5. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. the whole Chapter is but an <hi>Eulogie, Magnificat,</hi> and <hi>Landatory</hi> of our Sauiour, both as God and Man, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting him aboue the Angels, in his Perſon, and in his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and giuing him, among other, theſe prerogatiues; <hi>That he is ſet downe on the right hand of the Maieſtie on high,</hi> verſe 3. <hi>That he is made ſo much better than the Angels, as he hath by inheritance, obtained a more excellent name,</hi> verſe 4. <hi>That God neuer ſpake to the Angels, Thou art my Sonne, this day haue I begotten thee, and I will be to him a Father, and he ſhall be to mee a Sonne,</hi> verſe 5. But God ſaid concerning Chriſt, <hi>Let all the Angels of God worſhip him,</hi> verſe 6. <hi>They are his miniſters and inſtruments,</hi> verſe 7. He is a Iudge, an eternall Iudge; <hi>Thy Throne O God is for euer and euer,</hi> verſe 8. yea, not onely the naturall humane ſoule of our Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> bleſſed for euer; and the ſoule of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> full of grace, but euen our bodily nature in Chriſt, is lifted vp, aboue Angels, and Arch-Angels, Cherubims, or Seraphims, or any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8483:10"/>Creature of that Spirituall and Coeleſtiall Hierarchie.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>Adams</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, could not reach to Chriſt, and infect him. Chriſts <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> came home to <hi>Adam,</hi> and not onely ſaued his ſoule, but Chriſts Bloud on the Croſſe, <hi>beſprinkled the very graue of Adam;</hi> and whereas the firſt offence, had not power enough to deſtroy any one in this world, if they truſted in Chriſt; the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the ſecond <hi>Adam is not onely in the rigour of Gods iuſtice, ſufficient for the ſinnes of one world; but if GOD ſhould create more worlds of men, and all they be ſinners, and after ſinne, repentant and beleeuing in Chriſt, the ſuperabundant ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and treaſure of his merit, could not be ſpent: the fountaine of his Bloud would not be dried vp; they ſhould all be ſaued, and GOD must reſt indebted to the Croſſe: it hath payed for more than can ſinne, to the greateſt number of ſinnes and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that can be named by one; another man may make additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (for all Numeration is finite) but the Infinite merit of Chriſt can neuer be exhauſted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fifthly, if by the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> Goodneſſe was deſtroyed, not onely the ſame Goodneſſe, is by the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued; but euen the euils of puniſhment, yea of faultineſſe, <hi>mala poenae, &amp; mala culpae, mala vltoria, &amp; mala peccatoria,</hi> as they are phraſed by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> all, and euery one of theſe, turne to the behoofe and good of Gods children. For, <hi>we are Conquerours, wee are more than Conquerours, through him that loued vs, Rom.</hi> 8.37. For, many Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, through enuy, haue beene denyed Triumph; but we doe alwaies <hi>triumph in Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. And wee know, that <hi>all things worke together for good, to them that loue God, Rom.</hi> 8.38. Perſecution, Sickneſſe, Death, Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Sinne and Satan, ſhall by Chriſt profit vs. Let no man blame my prolixitie, nor cenſure me, for much commending of Chriſt, whom none diſcommendeth; for ſumming vp the gaine which wee haue by Him, which none would loſe. For loe, there ſtandeth before vs, in a habit penitentiall, and of a minde (I hope) moſt penitent, an hainous ſinner; who renounced Chriſt, fled from the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8483:11"/>glorious Enſigne of the Croſſe, which hee receiued in Baptiſme; diſclayming his portion in the ſecond Perſon of the indiuiduall Trinity, and in fact, if not in word, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing himſelfe an enemy to the ſonne of the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin full of grace; Ieſus Chriſt our onely Lord and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. O why didſt thou flye when thou wert captiue, from him, who was thy Redeemer? and being free in Chriſt, though in bodily durance, wouldeſt thou be taken cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue by Satan? and to auoid the ſlauerie of the little Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, the Turke, deuote thy ſelfe to the great Diuell the enemy of mankinde? By not adhering to Chriſt, by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thy beliefe, by diſclayming thy vow in Baptiſme, by profeſſing Turciſme, thou haſt ſold heauen, art initiated into hell, and haſt purchaſed onely a conſcience, frighted with horror, where the Worme ſtill gnaweth, and ſtill is hungry. Yea, whereas you thought to gaine by forſaking Chriſt, you haue forfeited all right, to all the creatures in heauen, and in earth. For, the true Chriſtian, by hauing Chriſt, hath an Intereſt in all things: <hi>All things are ours, and we are Chriſt's, and Chriſt is God's,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 3.33. And he that is without Chriſt though hee may haue, a right, <hi>in Fore terrene, &amp; humano;</hi> (for <hi>Dominium, non fundatur, in Gratiâ; ſed in Naturâ</hi>) and we allow Proprietie, ſo that the <hi>Meum</hi> of one Heathen, differeth from the <hi>Tuum</hi> of an other: Yet in <hi>Foro coeleſti, &amp; Diuino,</hi> Reuel. 5.11.—<hi>Many Angels, round about the Throne, or that Throne,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>with a lowd voyce,</hi> ſayd, <hi>Worthy is the Lambe, that was slaine, (namely our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt) to receiue, Power, Riches, and Wiſdome, and Strength, and Honour, and Glory, and Bleſſing; and euery Creature, which is in Heauen, and on the Earth, and vnder the Earth, and ſuch as are in the Sea, and all that are in them, not in eo</hi> as is the vulgat, but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, all the off-ſpring of all Creatures, ſaid, <hi>Bleſſing, Honour, Glory, and Power, be vnto Him that ſitteth vpon that Throne,</hi> (to diſtinguiſh him from others who ſate on other Thrones) <hi>and to the Lamb for euer and euer.</hi> They are all for Chriſt, and are Chriſts; and by Him, for vs; <hi>Wee being
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8483:11"/>called vnto the fellowſhip of Ieſus Christ our Lord.</hi> 1 Cor. 1.9. <hi>Co-heires with him,</hi> Rom. 8.17. And a reaſon hereof is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, verſe 32. <hi>If God ſpared not his owne Sonne, but deliuered him vp for vs all; how ſhal he not, with him alſo, freely giue vs all things?</hi> But all theſe things haue you loſt, (poore miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoule) by loſing Chriſt; and this great loſſe, doth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue the heinouſneſſe of thy ſinne, which is the next point in my propounded Method, to be handled.</p>
                  <p>For, though perchance you thought it, to be a ſmall offence, and it is muttered among ſome vnbeleeuers, or Misbeleeuers, as if this Penance were greater than the Fault, yet you will confeſſe, the mercifull indulgence of our Church, and the vglineſſe of this offence, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe fiue points.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that God hath loaded little ſinnes with heauie pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that thy ſinne, put into the ballance, weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth more, than the ſinne of <hi>Caine,</hi> or of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> or of the Iewes, which murthered Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that thy ſinne is made exceeding ſinfull, by beleeuing in ſo notorious a monſter as <hi>Mahomet</hi> was: And in his law, which is ſo full of beaſtly and ſenceleſſe lyes.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the exceeding ſinfulneſſe of thy tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is yet aggrauated, both from the excellencie of Chriſts perſon, whom thou didſt forſake, (He being the ſecond Perſon in Trinity, the Sonne of God, the holy Redeemer of man, the great <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>Angelus Foederis,</hi>) and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from the rationall verities of our Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly and laſtly, whereas by thy kindred, friends, or acquaintance, (in a fooliſh pittie, hurtfull to thy ſoule) falſe colours are ſet on bad cloth; faire painting on a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten boord; and ſome haue riſen vp in your defence, with ſemblances, to make thy ſinne ſhew leſſe; I intend (by Gods grace) in a holy ſeruitude, for the good of thy ſoule, and for the terrour of others, to plucke the figge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lcaues,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8483:12"/>to take away the excuſes, to remoue the looſe veiles and couers, that ſo you may ſee and bewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le the monſtrouſneſſe of your offence; and that others may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide the like.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, therefore you will eaſily confeſſe the fouleneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of your tranſgreſſion, if you remember that God doth all things <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; and being, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> neuer puniſhed beyond meaſure, any ſinne; but alwaies <hi>citra condignum;</hi> and yet ſhall behold the ſeueritie of Gods iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt <hi>ſmall treſpaſſes. The breach of the Sabbaoth was attended with death,</hi> Exod. 31.14. <hi>The gatherer of ſticke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in the Sabbaoth was put in Ward and then ſtoned,</hi> Numb. 15.34.
<note n="t" place="margin">
                        <hi>Moſes, capitali paenae ſubiecit ros, qui Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ium violarent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d potiſſimum de cauſâ, quòd Mundi creatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, Sabbathi violatione, in dubium reuocare viderentur, vt Kabbi Moſes Aegyptius ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bodin, in Methodo ſuâ, pag.</hi> 312.</note> 
                     <hi>Saul reiected for not destroying of Amalech,</hi> 1 Sam. 15 23. <hi>Vzza ſmote for his raſhneſſe,</hi> 2 Sam. 6.7. though he intended well. <hi>Aplague ſent to ſweepe a whole country, for Dauids numbring of the people,</hi> 2 Sam. 24.15. In the new Teſtament, <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> ſtrooken with ſudden death for a lye, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.3. The buyers and ſellers in the Temple caſt out and ſcourged with ſmall cords, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.14. though their actions were conducible, to the readier ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of ſacrifices in the Temple, S. <hi>Peter</hi> was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Satan,</hi> for giuing ill aduiſe, <hi>Math.</hi> 16.23. though, <hi>non odiendo Chriſtum, ſedſe nimis amando peccauit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">And not <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius</hi> alone (though <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donat</hi> ſaith ſo) but <hi>Chryſologus Sermone</hi> 27. (&amp; perchance ſome others, whom nor <hi>Maldonate,</hi> nor I euer read) more wittily, than ſoundly expound the words, thus; Dominus, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum poſt ſe mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. Scandalum remittit autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri: dicendo ad Petrum, Vade poſt me: &amp; Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo, Scandalum mihies.</note> And that which in application may ſtrike horror to our ſoules, the Figge-tree was curſed for bearing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but leaues, when the time of Figges was not <hi>yet</hi> come, <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.23. Theſe were iuſt rewards for ſmall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, for <hi>peccadillos</hi> in the eyes of men; but euery ſinne deſerueth death, euen the leaſt <hi>anomy,</hi> in the exactneſſe of Gods iuſtice. One mortall ſinne is not expiable with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeeres lying in the torments of hell. But this thy ſin, was not onely mortall, not onely a breach of thy vow in Baptiſme; but a flat Rebellious vnderſtanding of it: A trecherous oppoſition, a ſeandalous contradiction; ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ingrayning of the Chriſtal clere-ſauing water of Baptiſme, with the bloud of Circumciſion. Thy abiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of thy Sauiour, was an offence, almoſt beyond
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8483:12"/>Pardon, and aboue Indulgence; as may appeare, by a comparatiue Reference of ſome particulars, of thy Sinne, with others. In contemplation whereof, though ſome doe clippe thy ſinne, yet I dare ſay, That in diuerſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards, thy ſinne was greater, then that of <hi>Caines;</hi> He ſlew, but his Younger-Brother; but You haue ſlaine, as farre as you then could, <hi>the firſt borne of euery Creature, the Lord of Life; and haue crucified to your ſelfe againe, the Sonne of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame, Heb.</hi> 6.6. The bloud of <hi>Abel</hi> did cry againſt <hi>Caine: Vox ſanguinum cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantium fratris tui,</hi> Gen. 4.10. <hi>Vox ſeminum clamantium,</hi> ſaith the Chaldee; the voices of the little-ones, which might haue deſcended from <hi>Abel,</hi> in him, did cry againſt that vngracious Fatricide; yea, though <hi>Caine</hi> was branded all his life time, with vnuſuall bodily torment; and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht in his ſoule euer ſince, and all his poſteritie ſwept from the face of the earth in the floud; <hi>yet ſtill the bloud of</hi> Abel <hi>cryeth for vengeance, Heb.</hi> 11.4. as <hi>Aquin</hi> expounds it; and ſhall cry till the hand that ſtrake the blow, doe burne in fire and brimſtone; ſo <hi>Eſtius</hi> and <hi>Ribera.</hi> What puniſhment then did you deſerue, in betraying your El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-brother that offered vp a better ſacrifice than <hi>Abel,</hi> and would more profit you, than euer <hi>Abel</hi> would, or could haue profited <hi>Caine?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thy tranſgreſſion was greater then the ſinne of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> for he, only with a Politick eye, looking rather on the Sunne-riſing, then on the Sunne-ſetting, rebel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d againſt his Lord, and Maſter, <hi>Dauid;</hi> but you haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, yea arm'd your ſelfe, againſt <hi>Dauids</hi> Lord, and Maſter.</p>
                  <p>Thy Offence was greater, then diuerſe of the Iewes, who put our Redeemer vnto death; for, they did it through ignorance, as did alſo their rulers, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.17. But you wittingly againſt your owne Conſcience, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke your Sauiour; and though they praeferred <hi>Barabbas</hi> (who was a Robber <hi>Iohn</hi> 18.40. a Murtherer, <hi>Act,</hi> 3.14. a Mutiner, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.19.) yet you haue adhaered to one,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8483:13"/>euery way, worſe then <hi>Barrabas;</hi> before the moſt holy, iuſt, and innocent Chriſt, you haue aeſteemed <hi>Mahomet,</hi> that <hi>Rake-ſhame</hi> of the World, which was the third point propounded, and is now to be handled. <hi>Mahomet</hi> (I ſay) the <hi>Rauiſher</hi> of his Maſtreſſe,
<note n="u" place="margin">See <hi>Baronius ad Annum Chriſti,</hi> 630.</note> the known <hi>Adulterer</hi> with one <hi>Zeid,</hi> which he him-ſelf confeſſeth in his Law, and ſaith, God made it ſinne-leſſe, and exemplarie for euer: a <hi>Murtherer</hi> of the Emperours Brother: a <hi>Rebel</hi> againſt <hi>Heraclius,</hi> who was his <hi>Benefactor:</hi> a <hi>Gentile,</hi> in ſome pointes, a <hi>Iew</hi> in others, a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in others, a <hi>Maniche, Neſtorian;</hi> and <hi>Arrian;</hi> a very <hi>Compound</hi> of Hereſies; a Compounder of Vanities; a grand Impoſter, out of whom <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his <hi>Panoply,</hi> hath gathered, 130. Fables; and in whoſe <hi>Alcoran,</hi> there is ſuch an hotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potch of errors, that the ſight or ſmell, would ſurfet one. Errors palpable, as the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> darkneſſe: naſty, as bred in the lap of luſt; ſo brutiſh, ſo blockiſh, that, knowing all his vanities would he eaſily confuted, he cutteth off all diſputations, with the ſword; and in ſteede of Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Child of Truth diſplayed, he hath ſet Death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, to keepe them faſt in blindneſſe; yet in ſpight of worldly Policy, there haue broke-forth, ſeauentie two principall <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Sectes,
<note n="x" place="margin">See <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ulius Scaliger,</hi> againſt <hi>Exercitat,</hi> 258. <hi>Cardan, Sect.</hi> 2. which he borrowed from <hi>Ioannes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eo,</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Sandy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> from <hi>Scafiger.</hi>
                     </note> ſaith <hi>Iohannes Leo,</hi> in his third Booke, of his <hi>African Hiſtorie,</hi> And <hi>Leo</hi> was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time himſelfe a learned <hi>Mahumtan;</hi> but ſeeing, with the eyes of his minde, their abhominable Errors; and with the eyes of his Body, ſuch villany, as neuer was heard of, to be vpheld, by their ſuperſtitious Beleeſe, contrary to ſight, &amp; ſence, at one open Market in <hi>Alcair</hi> (as is in the ſame third booke) he bathed himſelfe, in the Lauer of Regeneration, and deteſting their Irreligion, became a Chriſtian. Likewiſe of late, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uerſe Turkes, haue ſealed their Profeſſion of Chriſtianitie, with their Blood, euen in <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> Yea a very Preiſt of their owne, a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous eminent Prieſt; <hi>Ibraim Sheck,</hi> was there ſtoned to death; his head after cut off, and his body burned, for preferring Chriſt before <hi>Mah<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>met.</hi> Diuers alſo of his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8483:13"/>Diſciples were beheaded, others were made Gally-ſlaues, for refuſing <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and adhering to Chriſt. Thus hath God his Chappell, or rather his <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans temple. Turkes who dye for Chriſt, will ariſe in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Chriſtians, who imbrace <hi>Mahomet.</hi> Who knoweth not, that the Turkes themſelues acknowledge Chriſt to be a Prophet, a great Prophet, a moſt holy man? triumphing, that they are Lords of the two Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, the one at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> the other at <hi>Mecha?</hi> I might enlarge, that almoſt incredible ſtory of <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> in the ſixteenth yeare of the Raigne of King <hi>Iohn:</hi> that the irreligious King offered to abandon Chriſt, and to ſticke faithfully to <hi>Mahomet;</hi> but the halfe religious Turke, the King of <hi>Morocco,</hi> gaue King <hi>Iohns</hi> Embaſſadors to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that if himſelfe had beene to chooſe a Religion, he would haue choſen to be a Chriſtian.</p>
                  <p>But ſmall inducements may not make one to ſhift the Religion he was borne in: and euery giddy-brain'd ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, is an vncompetent iudge in this caſe. I dare auow, of all the religions profeſſed vnder heauen, no profeſſion in the world hath more inſenſate fopperies, yea, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, than their <hi>Antilop,</hi> their <hi>Chymaera,</hi> their <hi>Coran,</hi> (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vſe and cuſtome will beare you out to call it their <hi>Alcaron.</hi>) Take a taſte of them.
<note n="y" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mahometus in Alcorano, dum vino &amp; maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè rubeo vellet gentibus ſuis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicere, ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ie in quolibet vuae rubeae grano ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitare vnum Diabolum: Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Montanus de Incantationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, pag.</hi> 200.</note> 
                     <hi>Mahomet</hi> taught, <hi>that euery red Grape had one diuell or more within it;</hi> but ſome haue found the diuell rather in Sacke, than Claret; and if they ſwallow the ſtones or kernels, when they eate the Raſins of the Sunne, they ſwallow many diuels. That the Angels and God, pray for <hi>Mahomet;</hi> which God, ſince they make but one perſon, to whom ſhall that perſon pray? That God ſweareth by the Diuels, where he eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the diuels to be greater than God. For all the world ſuppoſe, the things they ſweare by, to bee greater than themſelues. And <hi>Auerroes,</hi> that great Arabick Philoſopher, and <hi>Mahumetan</hi> thinketh there are no diuels.
<note n="z" place="margin">
                        <hi>Julius Scali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Exercitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one</hi> 355. and <hi>Auicen</hi> pallia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth their fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh lyes and ſenſuail Rules or Axiomes by expounding them Allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically.</note> And that <hi>Mahomet</hi> diuided the moone. I haue heard much of <hi>the man in the moone,</hi> and of the <hi>Buſh of bryars</hi> at his backe;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8483:14"/>which perchance, encrooked ouer to his Pole, and ſcratcht his necke, and made him a ſcald pate, <hi>That after this life they ſhall marry, and be giuen in mariage: that beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull</hi> Ganvmedes <hi>ſhall ſerue at the Table, and in a word, haue their fill of all be aſtiall corporeall pleaſures.</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">See all theſe chings punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally cited out of their <hi>Azoars,</hi> by <hi>Cardan de S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>btilitate, lib.</hi> 11. <hi>pag.</hi> 213.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The grand Epicure certainely, if he was not a Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of the Great Turke, yet would quickly haue tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his Religion. Is this a beliefe to be preferred before the Chriſtian? Then let Garlicke be valued before the Bread of Angels, the coeleſtiall Manna. Then let vs barter and exchange our Gold for Braſſe, our Pearles for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Stones; the Fruit of the Tree of Life, which is in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God, for the Apples of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> which being touched, vaniſh into aſhes. It is true, that the Turkes doe call themſelues <hi>Muſſelmans,</hi> that is, <hi>true beleeuers,</hi> (as euery Nation of the earth preſumes, they beleeue aright) yet ſince the Turkes refuſe the tryall of their Religion, by the touch-ſtone of Scripture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, euen of thoſe Scriptures which themſelues profeſſe; <hi>ſince the old Teſtament which they receiue,</hi> hath in a thouſand places prophecied of Chriſt: yea, all the Prophets, not onely from <hi>Samuel, Acts</hi> 3.24. but from <hi>Enoch,</hi> who was the ſeuenth from <hi>Adam, Iude</hi> 14. yea, in all faire probability, euen <hi>Adam</hi> prophecied of Chriſt, and in all certaintie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the expulſion out of Paradiſe, GOD himſelfe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpake to Satan, concerning Chriſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>I will put en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity betweene thy ſeed, and her ſeed: it ſhall bruize thy head, and thou ſhalt bruize his heele;</hi> which was really accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed on both ſides, when Chriſt was nayled to the Croſſe; the diuels inuiſibly on the other ſide of the Croſſe, ſaith <hi>Origen:</hi> I ſay, ſince God himſelfe fore-promiſed this, not of the ſeed of <hi>Adam,</hi> but of the ſeed of the woman; and that it cannot be interpreted of any other, but Chriſt, who was the onely Stone cut out of the rocke, without the helpe of mans hand, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.24. <hi>id eſt, abſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> coitu &amp; Semine humano, de Vtero virginali,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hierome</hi> on the place, and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> on Pſal. 99.5. (which according to the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint,</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:8483:14"/>and <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> is the 98. Pſalme) ſince the Turkes confeſſe this much of this,
<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Baronius ad Annum</hi> 630. thus of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, Chriſtum dicit verbum eſſe Dei, &amp; eius Filium; ſed Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atum &amp; Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum; Eúm<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur ex Maria, ſine ſemine gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum;</hi> adding, that the Iewes did crucifie Chriſts ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, but not Himſelfe.</note> and yet cannot bring one place in all the old Teſtament, that euer prophecied of <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let <hi>Mahomet</hi> be branded for a Iuggler, a Mount-bank, a beaſtiall people pleaſer; ingroſſing beliefe to him and his contrarie to Truth, Reaſon, or ſound Religion: which Miſ-beliefe he hath eſtabliſhed by the ſword, and not by Arguments; vpheld by violence and compulſion; or tempting allurements of the world; forcing, or deluding the ſoules of men, rather than perſwading by euidence of veritie. I cannot end yet with his perſon, but thus returne vnto it. That great ſeducer <hi>Mahomet,</hi> was a ſalacious Iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Amoroſo;</hi> and his intemperate laſciuiouſneſſe, was wayted on by infirmities and ſickneſſes correſpondent to his lewdneſſe. <hi>Hippocrates</hi> calleth <hi>Coitum,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>paruum morbum Comitialem;</hi> but he, for his luſt, and by it, was tormented with the Great-falling-ſickneſſe; and that diſeaſe, is a plague of an high-hand; and in him, a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of a very ſinfull ſoule, in a very ſinfull body. For, whereas <hi>it is appointed for all men to die once, Heb.</hi> 9.27. for that one firſt ſinne of <hi>Adam; Mahomet,</hi> who had ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſo great ſinnes, was ſtriken alſo with many deaths. For, what is the Falling-Sickneſſe, but a reduplication, a multiplication of death? He fell with paine, looked vgly, with a foming mouth, and wry-diſtorted countenance in his fits. He roſe with horror, like a pale carcaſe, and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme corpes, betweene the liuing and the dead. He was the But againſt which the Almighty ſhot his arrowes: bearing the image and figure of an Apoſtata in his body by relapſes; and the torments of a veſſell of wrath, in his ſoule, for his Impoſturage. Whoſe ſickneſſe is not ſo much denyed, as guilded ouer by his owne followers. And after death, he (promiſing to riſe againe) lay till he ſtanke, and his ſide was eaten with dogs, ſaith <hi>Eulogius</hi> the Martyr, (who liued the next age after) in his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:8483:15"/>
                  <p>But, (that I may come to the next point) as for our moſt holy, bleſſed, and glorious Saviour, Ieſus Chriſt, (O pardon me my Lord, for mentioning thy ſalutife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous names, when I am to confound that Rake-ſhame, and purge my lippes from the corruption they may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, in ſpeaking of ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h an hell-hound,) I ſay, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our gracious Redeemer, the Turkes themſelues doe not, they cannot ſay, that euer hee ſinned, or was ſicke; He healing all, and all manner of diſeaſes, had not one: His ſoule had her fulneſſe of grace: his bodily tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, was moſt pure. In his face, <hi>ſyderium quiddam illuxit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hierom.</hi> His whole body was <hi>ſpecioſum, quia forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum virtute Spiritus Sancti, in cuius opere, non poteſt eſſe error, aut defectus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lyra</hi> on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.</p>
                  <p>As for the Chriſtian Religion, it is moſt rationall, and accordant to the rectified Dictates of nature; and was planted in holy ſimplicitie, watered with the bloud, not of Murtherers, but of Martyrs, <hi>(Sanguis Martyrum, ſemen Eccleſiae)</hi> and whereas all other Religions haue decayed by Oppoſition, the Chriſtian Church gathereth ſtrength, and groweth vnder its Burden; being the pillar of truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Like an vpright pillar, is more ſtrong by hauing more weight vpon it.</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Graecam Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiam, ſi quiuis Magiſtratus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibuerit, ea ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim perit. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram autem Doctrinam, à primá vſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> eius Praedicatione, prabibent Reges, Duces, &amp; Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus, cum vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſis ſatelliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, illa tamen non flacceſcit, vt Doctrina huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, ſed magis floret. Clemens Alexand. Strom.</hi> 7. The quicke ſpreading of the Goſpell, may ſtop the mouthes of Saracens, and driue wonders into the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. It was like Lightning, which ſpreade it ſelfe all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, beyond ſence. And the publiſhing of it may be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Horſe-man, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 6.2. Who rode all abroad, and was victorious.</note> And is acknowledged to bee moſt agreeable vnto the generall, confeſſed Principles of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in both naturall and morall Philoſophie.
<note n="d" place="margin">As may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, cuiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by <hi>Clemens Alexand. Stro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I returne to the perſon of our bleſſed Sauiour Chriſt (of whom neuer good enough can be ſpoken) and reſume, that the Turkes themſelues, confeſſe him to haue beene a moſt holy Prophet, a worker of many wonders, greater than <hi>Moſes:</hi> that <hi>Pilate</hi> his Iudge pronounced him to be iuſt; that the people being beyond meaſure aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with his miracles, ſaid, <hi>Mark.</hi> 3.37. <hi>He hath done all things well.</hi> Hee was the wonder of men, not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: God and man, the Sonne of God; <hi>the brightneſſe of his glory, and the expreſſe image of his perſon, Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>The image of the inuiſible God, the firſt borne of euery creature; all things being created In him, and By
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8483:15"/>him, and for him, Coloſ.</hi> 1.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> In him, there, Chriſt is the cauſe-<hi>Ideal,</hi> or exemplary: By him, there, he is the cauſe <hi>Demiourgicall,</hi> or <hi>Architectonicall, not properly Inſtrumentall, but by indiuiſible Cooperation.</hi> For him, there, he is the cauſe ſupremely finall. I cannot ſay much of any of theſe, becauſe I intend to ſay ſomewhat of each. <hi>Moſes</hi> was admoniſhed of God, when he was about to make the Tabernacle: See, ſaith God, <hi>that thou make all things according to the Patterne ſhewed to thee in the Mount, Heb,</hi> 8.5. From which fore-ſight of <hi>Moſes, Plate</hi> tooke his <hi>Ideaes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iuſtin Martyr.</hi> Now, as the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle had an intellectuall <hi>eſſe,</hi> in the notion of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ere it had its <hi>eſſe</hi> materiall, and the forme of Artificials is firſt in the minde of the worke-man, before it is in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worke, ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle, Metaphyſ.</hi> 7. (though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where himſelfe is the greateſt Oppoſer, often times of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonicall <hi>Ideas,</hi> which he confuted but verbally, ſaith his greateſt defender <hi>Aquinas.</hi>) Likewiſe for naturall things of this world, I will ſay, as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did, to another purpoſe; <hi>Who dare ſay, that God doth any thing irrationabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Hee framed all things,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſaith <hi>Mercuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Triſmegiſtus;</hi> and the manner of making all things, was directed, as well by the Reaſon, as by the Power, of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Spirit, ſaith <hi>Anaxagoras.</hi> For, <hi>Recta ratio, eſt lex, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi Iouis,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Cicero</hi> 2. <hi>de Legibus.</hi> See this confirmed by Scriptures, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Eccloſiaſt.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Eſa,</hi> 40.12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.24. <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.15. The <hi>Idea</hi> of all things was in God, ere they were actually produced; and this <hi>Idea</hi> was Chriſt. <hi>For In him, were all things created,</hi> ſaith the Text, in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall.
<note n="e" place="margin">
                        <hi>Aquinas i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Coloſ.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Loco Jdearam nos habemus v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ſcilicet Verbum Dei-Artifexenim facit artificium ex hvc, quod fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit illud partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare formam apud ſe concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, &amp; fic Deus omnia in ſuá ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> pientia dicitur facere, quia Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientie Dei ſe habet adres creatas, ſicut ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> aedificatoris ad domum factam. Haec autem for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma &amp; Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia eſt Verbum, ideò omnia in ipſo condita ſunt, ſicut in quodam exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plari.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Created In Him and By Him</hi> (as by the efficient cauſe) <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1. at the latter end of the 16. verſe. <hi>All things were made by Him, Ioh.</hi> 1.3. And leſt the word <hi>(All)</hi> might be thought in this place, not to comprehend, the ſeuerally-ſingular parts of multitude (becauſe it doth not ſo other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where) the Apoſtle addeth remarkably, <hi>And without Him was not any thing made, that was made.</hi> Where he intimateth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8483:16"/>that God made not the world by Chriſt, as the workeman doth the worke, by the Phyſicall inſtrument, (for this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth of Arrianiſme) but that Chriſt was indiuiſibly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>working with the Father: yea, all the workes of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>quoad extra, ſunt indiuiſa.</hi> Againe, it is not ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; <hi>nothing was made,</hi> but in a more emphaticall phraſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>not one thing, not any thing;</hi> by which the Diuinity of our bleſſed Sauiour is cleerely proued. So <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. <hi>By Chriſt, God made the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, all things were created not onely, <hi>in him,</hi> and <hi>by him,</hi> but <hi>for</hi> him. And though, concerning his humane nature, <hi>We are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods,</hi> 1. Cor. 2.23. <hi>and the Head of euery man is Chriſt, and the Head of Chriſt is God,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.3. yet, in regard of his Diuinity, <hi>He is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to his Father;</hi> yea, <hi>all things were created for Him:</hi> As he is the Mediator betweene God and man, <hi>God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him heire of all things,</hi> Heb. 1.2. <hi>Deus ipſe ſine Chriſto, idolum eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian:</hi> God is worſhipped with falſe worſhip, if he be not worſhipped through Chriſt. And I, for my part, ſolemnly profeſſe, <hi>I deſire not heauen, or ioyes thereof, without Him. Whatſoeuer wee doe in word or deede, let vs doe it in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, Coloſ.</hi> 3.17. Our prayers are then accepted, when they are cloſed, either with his Prayer, or with his Name. Yea, alwaies reiected and turned into ſinne, if there be not euermore, a <hi>tacit</hi> or implicite reference to Him: yea, an actuall expreſſion of Him, and imploring his aide, when we are lifted vp by Deuotion, or caſt downe by Temptation: of which more at large by and by. O that thou hadſt obſerued this, and called vpon Chriſt when thou waſt tempted! Hee hath promiſed, <hi>I will not faile thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> Therefore, ſilly ſeduced ſoule, it was the height of the ſinne, that thou didſt forſake Him; <hi>Him who is the Fountaine of liuing waters, and haſt hewed out, for thy ſelfe, Ciſternes, broken Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternes that can hold no water, Ier.</hi> 2.13. Theſe Ciſternes are thy excuſes, pretenſions, motiues, or falſe guides, which ſeduced thee; and theſe come now in order to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8483:16"/>laid open. Whereas thou haſt ſaid it, and (as I heare) ſworne it, and others with thee, and for thee, <hi>That thou wert circumciſed by extreame force,</hi> and therefore thou ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, thou haſt not loſt Chriſt, that they rauiſhed thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but not thy Beliefe, That thou didſt ſtriue, till thou couldeſt ſtriue no longer, againſt their violence; and then with humble patience, wert content to dye vnder their hands: I muſt needs ſay (if ſo it were) thou were then a glorious Confeſſor; and if thou hadſt dyed then, vnder their butcherie, Thou hadſt waſhed thy robes in the bloud of the Lambe; Thou hadſt ſhined as the Sunne in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, and beene one of the primeſt Saints in heauen. For, though euery one ſhall haue the Penny of eternall happineſſe, called in <hi>Aquins Supplement, aurea:</hi> and the Eſſentials of heauenly bliſſe, are neither more nor leſſe, but euery one ſhall poſſeſſe enough, to his full content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a ſurpluſſage be remaining: (for, the entring into the Maſters ioy, ſuppoſeth the ioy to be greater and larger, than he that entreth; as the houſe is greater than its inhabitant, and <hi>continens maius contento:</hi>) yet the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentals of Beatitude, may be more or leſſe: one may haue more Talents, more Cities, than another; Virgins and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious Paſtors haue their <hi>Aureolas</hi> aſſigned them by the Schoole; but the Martyrs reward is ſimply aboue the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reolae</hi> of Teachers, or Virgins (as it is in <hi>Aquins</hi> Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 96. <hi>Articul.</hi> 12. I dare not ſay with <hi>Gerſon, per Martyrium, deletur in proprio ſanguine, quaelibet culpa, ſimul &amp; poena:</hi> yet I hold it probable, that what <hi>grace ſoeuer a man had before, if he loſt it by ſinne,</hi> he ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies and wholly recouer it, by Martyrdome: ſo holdeth <hi>Scotus</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentia, Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>Diſput.</hi> 7. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 6. <hi>Punct.</hi> 10. <hi>in fine:</hi> and certaine, with <hi>Caietan, That an vniuerſall abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution from ſinne and puniſhment, is giuen in the preception of Baptiſme and Martyrdome: in primam part. Thom. Quaeſt.</hi> 68. <hi>Artic.</hi> 2. Giuen, I ſay, by God, for Chriſts ſake: in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, for the preſent eſtate; in Martyrdome, for euer: ſo that he preſently mounteth vp to indicible ioyes of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8483:17"/>heauen. A Martyr is a Scale and Signet on the finger of the All-mightie; One of the maſter-pieces of GODS worke: a Rubie of Chriſts Crowne; moſt pretious is his death. Oh that thou hadſt then dyed, thou hadſt beene a perfect Martyr! Thy cauſe was good; thy willingneſſe to ſuffer, rather than to abiure (as is reported of thee) was good: if death had preſently enſued, Thou hadſt beene a conſummate Martyr.</p>
                  <p>Theſe two next Sections were not preached, by reaſon of the ſtraitneſſe of time, yet thought fit to be inſerted.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt, <hi>Non Poena, ſed Cauſa, facit Martyrium,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> and after him, the gloſſe on the Pſalmes: and not all that are perſecuted, but <hi>they</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>which ſuffer perſecution for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake, are bleſſed, Math.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Auguſtine ad Bonifacium, Epiſt.</hi> 50. <hi>Dominus cum latronibus crucifixus est; ſed quos Paſſio iungebat, cauſa ſeparabat. Idem in Pſal.</hi> 42. <hi>poteſt eſſe impiorum ſimilis poena, ſed diſſimilis eſt Martyrum Cauſa.</hi> And one may be a Martyr, not onely for points <hi>de fide,</hi> but <hi>Omnium virtutum Opera, ſecundùm quod referuntur in Deum, ſunt quaedam Proteſtationes fidei, per quam nobis inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſcit, quòd Deus, huiuſmodi opera, à nobis requirit, &amp; nos pro eis remunerat, &amp; ſecundùm hoc, poſſunt eſſe Martyrij cauſa; vnde &amp; beati Ioannis Baptiſtae Martyriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in Ecclcſiâ celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, qui non pro negandâ Fide (Aquinas</hi> ſhouldſay, <hi>pro defenſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne fidei</hi> or to the like ſence) <hi>fed pro reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſione Adulterij mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>em ſuſtinuit, Aquin.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">ae</hi>. <hi>queſt.</hi> 124. <hi>artic.</hi> 5. <hi>in corpore Artic.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Concerning the ſecond point neceſſarie to Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, It is a prompt and willing minde to ſuffer. The good Thiefe was not a Martyr, in reſpect of his Cauſe, but in regard of his Alacrity to dye for Chriſt, we may ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him, at large. He that is haled to death grudgingly, is no Martyr, though he were put to true death, for the chiefeſt point of faith. But he who is prompt and forward to ſuffer, though the exceſſiueneſſe of torment doe choke and ſwallow vp the exerciſe of Reaſon and Sence: ſo that the Patient feeleth no paine, nor knoweth any thing in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8483:17"/>his extremitie; yea, though he hath not in the act of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, any preſent actuall intention to dye; yet, ſince, as a deſigned Martyr, he might praecogitate thus, <hi>I reſolue to endure and ſuffer not onely, whilſt I doe know my miſerie, and feele my paine: but when paine hath tyrannized ouer, both my knowledge and my ſence, till I haue grappled with death:</hi> I ſay, this mans ſuffering is the effect of his intention, and his intention continueth virtually in the effect: He is a true glorious conſummate Martyr. That the vſe of reaſon may be ouercome in a tranſcendent paſſion, is vnqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Ipſo momento temporis, quo ad voluptatis peruenitur ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremum, poenè omnis acies, &amp; quaſi vigilia cogitationis obruitur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine, de Ciuit.</hi> 14.16 And not onely <hi>poenè,</hi> but Delight ſtealeth away the intellect of a wiſe man, ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle, Ethic.</hi> 7.9. yea, if one ſhould be created and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, in the height of any kinde of pleaſure, and not be ſurfetted nor abated of it, he would neuer haue one wiſe thought, and I ſhould not thinke him to be a reaſonable creature. For, Reaſon is drowned in Pleaſure. Much more eaſily may the vſe of Reaſon be deuoured by paine: for we ſee the faireſt beaſts, frighted from their chiefeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, by feare of paine. <hi>Nemo eſt qui non magis dolorem fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giat</hi> (the Schooles reade it amiſſe, when they cited it, <hi>luge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at) quàm appetat voluptatem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine, in lib. Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginta-trium Quaeſt; Quaeſt.</hi> 36. Now then, as he, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth Fornication, if, in the moment of his deareſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, he vſeth neither Reaſon nor Will, yet ſinneth (ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe,) and that mortally, becauſe he expoſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to a Paſſion, in which he cannot vſe Reaſon, ſaith <hi>Scotus, Sentent.</hi> 3. <hi>Diſtinct.</hi> 15. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 1. <hi>circa medium:</hi> ſo in the paſſion Martyrs, if exceſſiue paine doe prey vpon the intellect, and the ſence, leauing them for the time, both ſenceleſſe &amp; vnintelligent, yet is the Crowne due to their heads, as to an Act of Fortitude, <hi>elicitiuè,</hi> their minde being confirmed by it, and as to an Act of charitie <hi>impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuè. For, greater charitie none hath, than this, that a man lay downe his life, Ioh.</hi> 15.13. <hi>Faulus Diaconus</hi> writeth of S. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:8483:18"/>that he anſwered the Pro-Conſul <hi>Galerius</hi> thus, <hi>Conſultum mihi meliùs eſſe non quaero, quàm vt Deum meum adorans ad ipſum totâ mentis Auiditate feſtinem:</hi> and hee addeth, <hi>Ceruicem obtulit gladio.</hi> I cannot paſſe by what S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Epist.</hi> 9. <hi>ad Martyres &amp; Confeſſores,</hi> ſaith of the admirable reſolutions of primitiue Martyrs, <hi>ſtete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ſerui Chriſti voce liberâ, mente incorruptâ, virtute diuinâ, telis quidem ſaecularibus nudi, ſed armis Fidei credentes arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. Steterunt torti torquentibus fortiores, ac pulſantes ac lani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antes vngulas, pulſata &amp; lanitata membra vicerunt. Inexpug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabilem fidem, ſuperare non poterat, ſaeuiens diu plaga repetita: quamuis, ruptâ compage viſcerum, torquerentur inſeruis Dei, iam, non membra, ſed vulnera. Fluebat ſanguis, qui incendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Perſecutionis extingueret; qui flammas &amp; ignes Gehennae glorioſo cruore ſopiret.</hi> Concerning the third requiſite to Martyrdome, it is bodily Death. <hi>Mors est de ratione Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrij,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">â</hi> 2ae. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 124. <hi>Artic.</hi> 4. not onely <hi>Mors in facto eſſe,</hi> but <hi>Mors in fieri. Inflictio Mortis</hi> (as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin</hi> tearmeth it) ſo that death follow. <hi>Auguſtine de Ciuit.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Dictum eſt homini, morieris, ſi peccaueris: nunc dicitur Martyri, morere, ne pecces.</hi> The priſon, with all its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, of chaynes, hunger, cold, and inſtruments of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious tortures, make not a perfect Martyr, if hee ſuruiue, vnleſſe ſuruiuing a while, he dye of the paines, torments, or wounds inflicted. I confeſſe, S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> writeth <hi>ad Martyres,</hi> and they were liuing: So <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, there were <hi>deſignati Martyres; iam inter Martyres deputandi,</hi> as <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cianus</hi> the Confeſſor, ſaith to <hi>Celerinus</hi> the Confeſſor. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian Epiſt.</hi> 25. <hi>part.</hi> 1. maketh mention of ſuch, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt in trouble, gaue good example of vertue, and were honoured, equally with Martyrs: for their hands made the Crownes, and they dranke the cup of Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their Brethren: and yet he ſets a trauerſe betweene them, and others, who did vndergoe <hi>Conſummata Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> as he calleth them, which is by death onely.</p>
                  <p>A glorious Saint would haue reioyced to ſit at thy feete in heauen: thou hadſt come neerer to Chriſt, than milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8483:18"/>of bleſſed Spirits: and perchance, by ſo much neerer, than ſome Angels, by how much the more thou reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bledſt Chriſt, by being baptized, in the Baptiſme of bloud for his glory, (which the Angels cannot doe) as Chriſt dyed to ſaue and glorifie thee: But, if thou wert not forced, if thy tongue, or thy heart conſented to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion; if thou didſt put any truſt in it, (for we haue heard and read, that the Turkes compell none to their Religion; and that <hi>Mahomet</hi> left this rule to his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to ſay vnto them, who differed from them in profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; <hi>Let me haue my Law, and take you, yours; you are free from that which I doe, and I am likewiſe free from that which you doe.</hi>) I ſay, if thou heldeſt vp thy finger, or didſt caſt away thy hat, or ſufferedſt thy ſelfe to be drencht with <hi>Opium,</hi> or exchangeſt the markes of thy profeſſion, or by vſing any other abiuring trickes, or initiating ceremonies to that helliſh irreligion, like other Renegadoes (which, as we hope, you did not at firſt; ſo we are vncertaine whether you did or no) thy Repentance had neede ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount thy Penance, and many teares muſt flow from thine eyes to waſh thoſe ſinnes away.</p>
                  <p>From thy excuſe, that thou wert forced to conforme thy ſelfe, which is one of the Ciſternes, which not we, but God muſt try, whether it will hold water or no; let mee come to thoſe faults, for which (I am ſure) thou haſt no iuſt excuſes. You went in Turkiſh-guiſe, your apparrell proclaimed you to be a Turke, at leaſt in ſemblance; the exchanging of your ordinarie clothing for the Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan you cannot deny, you were ſeene and taken in it, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken (I heare ſay) willingly to come to our ſide, but taken in ſuch an attire as did diſcriminate you from a Chriſtian; you cannot ſay, that daily they put on thoſe clothes; you haue publikely confeſſed, your yeelding to their allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, rather than to their violence. <hi>Habemus confitentem Reum.</hi> Oh why beginning in the Spirit, whilſt they mang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thy fleſh, didſt thou end in the fleſh, by ſubiecting thy ſpirit vnto them! Indeed God commanded the Iewes,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8483:19"/>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Thou ſhalt make thee fringes on the foure quarters of thy Veſture. They ſhal weare fringes &amp; blew Ribbaend, Numb.</hi> 15.38. as Memorials and Remembrances of their Duties. The Scribes and Phariſees would ouer-doe the matter, and make broad their Philacteries, and enlarge <hi>the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of their Garments, Mat.</hi> 23.5. Likewiſe the Chriſtians in the Primitiue Church diſtinguiſhed themſelues from Gentiles, <hi>by wearing the Cloake, and not the Gowne;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that cuſtome taken vp, the Cloake was in high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                        <hi>Super omnes exuuias &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plos, Auguſta veſtis; ſuper<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> omnes apices &amp; titulos.— Suadeo reuerere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> habitum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian.)</hi> Againe, <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de pallij bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ium eſt; ſub cuius recogitatu improbi mores <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>èl erubeſcunt. —Gaude pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium &amp; exulta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> melior iam te philoſophia dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata eſt, ex quo Chriſtianum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtire caepiſti, Tertul.</hi> in his Booke <hi>de Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio.</hi>
                     </note> as a badge of humility, as a ſigne of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Philoſophers, imitating, yea, out-going the ancient Greeke Philoſophers, in ſimplicitie and honeſtie, as farre as they did, the warlike and bloudy Romans: whoſe Gownes betokened Lordly Domineering, <hi>and were lined with pride, though fringed with
<note n="g" place="margin">Calcei, propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Togae tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundiſſima pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum tutela, Tertul. ibid.</note> durt.</hi> Cauſe there was, and good cauſe, for the Iew and the Chriſtian, of thoſe times, to profeſſe their Religion, by their very Apparell. But the Turkiſh Turbant was naſtic in the cauſe, ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in the vſe. <hi>Mahomet,</hi> beſides that he was an vnhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome man, and his whole race to this day, the ill-fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redſt, that are ſeene in the world, deſcending from one man; among many other foule diſeaſes, was alwaies pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued, not onely with a Scabbed head, but a Scald pate,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>h</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>George Sandys,</hi> in the firſt Booke of his Trauailes.</note> which occaſioned himſelfe (as ſome ſay) to weare a white Shaſh (woollen would haue made his ſcald pate ſorer) therefore his Turbant was of linnen; a faire out-ſide, for a purulent and ſtinking inſide: And his followers muſt doe as he did, though they goe to the diuell as hee did. The preſent vſe, euen as they intend it, is full of ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous folly. They will haue no haire on their head, except one locke on the top of their crowne, (ſo perhaps had their <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who was a man of much Matter, and of Running head) and by this locke, they hope to be lifted vp to Paradiſe; and this they couer, as the reſt of their head, with a Turbant. Men beſotted, not knowing the power of death, conſuming their locke at length: nor the power of the Reſurrection, which abhorreth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8483:19"/>ſo vnnaturall and deformed a ſight.</p>
                  <p>To this thy great fault of wearing Veſtures, of Turkiſh faſhion, didſt thou adde a greater of bearing Armes againſt Chriſtians, in one of the Turkiſh ſhippes. Would you fight vnder the Banner of the <hi>Halfe-Moone,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Streamer of the Croſſe of Chriſt? and liue as a Bird of prey, in a man of Warre, and a Piraticall Thiefe of the ſea, vpon moſt innocent and oppreſſed Chriſtians? What had Chriſt deſerued at thy hands, that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt turne thy weapons againſt thy Countrymen, friends, and kindred, againſt Chriſt himſelfe in his members? Any bloud of the Chriſtians, ſhed by thy aſſiſtance, will not be waſhed from thee, but by a fountaine of teares; for a little bloud diſcoloureth much water: no purple is ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing, in-growne and laſting, as the purpured bloud of Innocents: And when thou haſt wept, whil'ſt thou canſt weepe, yet then vtter the prayer of the Prophet, <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> 9.1. <hi>Oh that my head were waters, and mine eyes a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of teares.</hi> Chriſt himſelfe ſhed three ſorts of teares, <hi>Teares of compaſſion on Hieruſalem, Luk.</hi> 19.41. Oh powre forth thou the like, for thoſe that are in any miſery. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion is aboue a common gift; for one giueth himſelfe by it; <hi>magis dat, quiſe dat, quàm, qui de ſuis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregorie.</hi> The ſecond ſort of teares, which Chriſt ſhed, were <hi>teares of good will:</hi> when <hi>Lazarus</hi> was dead, and Chriſt ſaw <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> weepe, and the Iewes weepe, hee wept alſo, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.35. whence perhaps proceeded that iniunction (that we might be like to our Sauiour) <hi>Weepe with them that weepa, Rom.</hi> 12.15. Thirdly, there ſtreamed from Chriſt, <hi>teares of compunction recorded, Heb.</hi> 5.7. not for ſins (or if for ſins, for our ſinnes, not any one of his, who had none) but, when he was in feare or danger. Follow thy Sauiour, thy guide, thy deliuerer; powre forth teares of compunction. There is no branch of thy offence, but muſt be laued and bathed in teares, and the ſpot ſoked-out, by weeping. Euen thy partaking with Turkes againſt the Armes of Chriſtians, though ſome, (who themſelues are ſuſpected, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> have beene faulty, as you weare) doe ſleighten the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8483:20"/>offence, muſt coſt thee many a ſigth, many a bitter ſobbe, many a prayer, and fruits of good workes worthy of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. For thy ſoules ſake, I deſire thee, labour not to leſſen thy fault; ſay not, Thou didſt, what thou didſt, to a good end, <hi>viz.</hi> in hope to eſcape their furious vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tyranny. Thou didſt forget thine old leſſon, though it be the Pearle, the Crowne, the Glory of Chriſtianitie, <hi>Their damnation was iuſt, who did</hi> (but) <hi>affirme, that</hi> S. <hi>Paul did ſay, Let vs doe euill, that good may come, Rom.</hi> 11.8. More gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uouſly may they be damned, who doe euill, that good may come. A Chriſtian ought to hate ſinne, with ſo perfect an hatred, that he ought not to commit one ſinne for all the pleaſures of the earth, nor for all that Satan offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto Chriſt, in his vaunting lye, <hi>viz. for all the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the world, and the glory of them.</hi> Yea, if it could be poſſible, that the Kingdome of heauen, and the ioyes thereof ſhould be propounded, as a reward, for the acting of one ſinne, we ought not to doe that one ſinne, for to purchaſe Heauen; and I had farre rather be, as Chriſt was, in hell, without ſinne, than in heauen with the ioyes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Iude</hi> verſe 6. as ſome Angels were with ſinne.</p>
                  <p>I come to thy falſe-guides, and moſt ſilly motiues that enſnared thee, and they were, (as I haue beene informed) theſe three; firſt, the example, with the perſwaſion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Renegadoes: ſecondly, the ſenſe and feeling of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent miſerie, with the feare of worſe to come: thirdly, the baites and allurements of immunitie preſent, and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity promiſed. Againſt all, and euery of which, thou ſhouldeſt haue beene armed with a Chriſtian Panoply.</p>
                  <p>The example of other Reuolters, ſhould rather haue terrified, than perſwaded you; ſince ſome turne for ſpleen, others for gaine, the moſt for feare, none for conſcience ſake. <hi>Cherſeogly</hi> became an Apoſtata, to be reuenged of his father, who had taken his wife from him, amidſt the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie of marriage. <hi>Vlacciali</hi> denyed the faith, to plague his fellow-gally-ſlaue, who called him Scald-pate. Like will to like; Scald-pate to Scald-pate; <hi>Vlacciali</hi> to <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:8483:20"/>Others change Faith for Gaine; and here the trecherous villany of Factors, is notorious; who being intruſted with much goods of their maſters, turne Turkes, to be maſters of thoſe goods; deſtroying their ſoules to cozen the honeſt-braue Merchants-Aduenturers. Among all the Reuolters in <hi>Africa,</hi> you cannot name one, who whileſt he was of our profeſſion, ſerued God daily, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Chriſt duly, liued conſciouſly, euidencing his fruitfull faith, by multitude of charitable workes. But, ſuch as are among vs, though not of vs; ſuch as are to chooſe Religion; <hi>Ambo-dexters, Nulli-fidians,</hi> ſuch <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phibia,</hi> as can liue, both on Land and Water, or ſuch as haue ſtayned their ſoules with ſome blacke ſinnes: theſe are the Chamelions which will change colour with euery ayre, and their beliefe, for matters of ſmall moment. A Sparrow will be taught to imitate the exquiſite melody of the Nightingale; but ſhe will chirpe at the end, ſaith the learned <hi>Andrew Libauius.</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>Nemo poteſt fictam perſonam diu ſuſtinere: <hi>and</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Deſinit in piſcem mulier formoſa ſupernè,</l>
                     </q> may be the Mottoes of Hypocrites. In point of imitation, we are to follow the beſt men, not the worſt, ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, in Pſal.</hi> 39. He who of his owne deuoire without a patterne doth well, is beſt to be approued; he, who ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the firſt, not in time or place, but in worth, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the former his ſampler, deſerueth the next eſteeme. Contrarily, he that leades the way in euill, is guiltie of a great offence; but he, of a greater, who is a follower of euill example:
<note n="i" place="margin">
                        <hi>Auguſtine in Pſal.</hi> 108. on thoſe words, <hi>peccatum matris eius non delea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> thus; <hi>Quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum Bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Jmitatio, ſacit, vt etiam propria peccata del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>antur; ſic malorum imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio facit, vt non ſolùm ſua, ſed etiam malorum quos imitati ſunt, merita ſortiantur.</hi>
                     </note> for he would not take warning by his brothers fall, which he would haue done; and as he is an Ape of one precedent, ſo is he a leader and drawer on of others, which he ſhould not be. Nor are you to follow good men alone, but good men, onely in good things. Follow not <hi>Noah</hi> in Drunkenneſſe; <hi>Dauid</hi> in Adultery, and Murther; S. <hi>Peter</hi> in Deniall of his Maſter. <hi>Follow not that which is euill, but that which is good, in the</hi> 3. <hi>Epiſt. of</hi> S. <hi>Iohn, verſe</hi> 11. <hi>Be yee followers of me, euen as I am of</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:8483:21"/>Chriſt, ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Be ye followers of God. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 5.1. and that muſt needes be in all goodneſſe onely.</p>
                  <p>I paſſe ouer to the next branch, The perſwaſions of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negadoes. <hi>Iudah</hi> cannot want an Adullamite, his friend in ſhew, to carry to <hi>Thamar,</hi> her promiſed gifts, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.20. nor <hi>Ammon</hi> a ſubtile <hi>Ionadab,</hi> to draw him to villany, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.5. And there will ſtill ſtart vp a man of Belial, a <hi>Sheba,</hi> to blow a Trumpet, and ſay, <hi>We haue no part in Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.1. All theſe, and the like, are recounted for our terrour; that we might auoid the Inticers, Broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and Panders vnto ſinne; and what ſaith the Word of God; <hi>My ſonne, if ſinners intice thee, conſent thou not, Pro.</hi> 1.10. Firſt, perchance they told thee, <hi>That he who doth, as moſt doe, feweſt will finde fault with him: and that there are more Turkes than Chriſtians.</hi> By the ſame reaſon, a Turke muſt turne Gentile and Pagan; becauſe <hi>euen at this day, there are more Infidels than Mahumetans.</hi> Goe not by num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, goe by weight. <hi>Profer ſtateram &amp; appende:</hi> bring forth thy ballance, and weigh; and ſee, that much chaffe is weighed downe by a few graines of good corne: <hi>the narrow and vneuen path, leadeth to life; the broad way to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> Secondly, perhaps they told thee, Thou mighteſt keepe thy conſcience ſafe and ſtedfaſt, and GOD placed neuer a bone in thy tongue, but thou mighteſt turne it at thy pleaſure: O blinde guides, leaders of the blinde! euen iuſt like him, who ſaid, <hi>Iuravi linguâ, mentem iniuratam ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro.</hi> This hypocricie is a double ſinne, <hi>quia. &amp; iniquitas eſt, &amp; ſimulatio. Diſſembling of Religion, comes neere hereſie; Tam pro iniquitate occultâ, quàm pro incredulitate apertâ.</hi> The Heart is the Father, the Mouth is the Mother of ſpeech: if there be guile or hypocriſie, the iſſue is adulterous. Did not God frame thy body, as well as thy ſoule? <hi>Thou wert to preſent thy body, a liuing ſacrifice, holy and acceptable vnto God; and this is your reaſonable ſeruice, Rom.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy ſoule, and with all thy minde, and with all thy ſtrength, Mark.</hi> 12.30. Where, all the parts and faculties of the ſoule, and body
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8483:21"/>are vnderſtood.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>k Praecipetur no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, vt noſtra tota Intentio, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur in Deum, quod eſt, Ex toto Corde; &amp; quòd Intellectus noſter ſubdatur Deo, quod eſt Ex toto mente; &amp; quòd Appetitus noſter, reguletur ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dùm Deum, quod eſt Ex totâ Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ; &amp; quòd, Exterior actus noſter, obediat Deo, quod Eſt, ex totâ fortitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, vel virtute, vel viribus Deum diligere, Aquin.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. 2<hi>ae. Queſt.</hi> 45. <hi>Artic.</hi> 5. <hi>in Corpore.</hi>
                     </note> He likes not the halfe ſeruice of the Soule alone, he loues the whole-burnt-Offering. All is too little that we can do, that we can giue. <hi>Cauſa diligendi Deum, Deus eſt; Modus, ſine modo diligere,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> And that Charity is commanded, which is, out of a pure heart, and a good Conſcience, and Faith vnfained 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. But thy heart was not pure, thy Conſcience was er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious, thy Faith was feined. When they tempted, thou ſhould'ſt haue praied: In a great ſuggeſtion, when one is cunningly ſet vpon, to forſake his Sauiour, it is a new ſinne, a ſinne, <hi>Vaſtans Conſcientiam,</hi> ſhip-wracking a good Conſcience, <hi>Then,</hi> not to call actually on Chriſt; then, not to Loue God, aboue all thinges. The affirmatiue Precept bindes not, at all times, alike, and on all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</p>
                  <p>But, firſt, When we are deuoutly muſing or reuoluing, of Gods Loue and Fauours, of old, beſtowed on vs. Fauours, either poſitiue, or priuatiue; belonging, either to this life, or to the life eternall.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, When at the preſent; we receiue from the hand of God, ſome ſingular Bleſſing, concerning, the publike, or our owne particular.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, When a man of Diſcretion, receiueth, either of the Sacraments.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, When a man is Contrite, and humbled extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily, by the ſight of his ſinnes; or deſireth <hi>the vnual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable benefit of Preiſtly Abſolution.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fiftly, When God's Honor is quaeſtioned, or his Name blaſphemed.</p>
                  <p>Sixtly, When we are at any ſolemne Exerciſe, of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in any place.</p>
                  <p>Seuenthly, When priuately, we are in a ſerious delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſpeculation, and Contemplation of things diuine.</p>
                  <p>Eightly, When one is very ſicke, or approaching to his Graue, or thinkes he lieth on his Death-bed.</p>
                  <p>Ninthly and laſtly. Though death be farre of, if when we are terribly tempted, inwardly, or out-wardly; either
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8483:22"/>by our owne Concupiſcence, or by Satan, or by his Agents, if we doe not practiſe at theſe times, eſpecially, according as we vowed in Baptiſme, (that is) if we renounce not then, aboue other times, the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>World</hi> and the <hi>Deuill.</hi> If we do not then, feruently Pray; then actually implore Chriſt's ayde: if we doe not then, really <hi>Loue God aboue all things, ſummè, appreciatiue, and vnite our ſelues to him, with all our Heart, Soule, Minde and ſtrength, we are debtors to that Law, Damnation is our Due, in Rigore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>l</hi> You may ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ome of theſe points, imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly handled, by <hi>Nauarrus,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Manual:</hi> by <hi>Sotus, de Naturâ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Gratiâ,</hi> 2.22 by <hi>Valentian</hi> on <hi>Aquins Summ: Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>Diſput.</hi> 3. <hi>Quaeſt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uncs.</hi> 1.</note> In theſe things, when you were tempted, you were faultie: you called not on God, though he ſaid, <hi>Call vpon me, in the time of trouble:</hi> you ſought not for Comfort of Chriſt, who proclaymed, <hi>Come vnto me, all ye that be heauy laden, and I will refreſh you:</hi> you did not adhaere, to your firſt loue, nor cleaue vnto your Sauiour. For theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardes, among other, thou wert iuſtly (for a time) forſaken of God.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond motiue might be, The ſight, of others Freedome, and the ſence, of thy Miſery, their Credit, thy Chaines, without hope of help; thy praeſent Paine, and Feare of future worſe harmes. Oh, but thou ſhouldeſt haue remembred, what Chriſt charged thee, Mat. 10.28. <hi>Feare not thoſe, which kill the Body, but are not able to kill the Soule; but feare him, who is able, to deſtroy, both Body, and Soule, in hell.</hi> Thou ſhould'ſt alſo haue call'd to minde, what is ſaid, <hi>Iames</hi> 1.2, <hi>Count it all ioy, when yee fall into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe Temptations; know that the Trying of your faith, worketh Patience; and let Patience haue her perfect worke. For it is thank-worthy, if a man, for Conſcience ſake toward God, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure greife; ſuffering wrongfully,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 2.19. Which hee diuinely eſtabliſheth, by our Calling, and by the Example of Chriſt. A thouſand places may be added, bending towards this point.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">As, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.3, <hi>&amp;.</hi> 7. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>erſes</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2. <hi>Act.</hi> 14, 21. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22, 42. <hi>Rom</hi> 8, 18. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.27. and the whole Army of Confeſſors or Martyrs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11 For, <hi>Reprobus tam alienus exiſtit à verbere, quàm extraneus erit ab haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate;</hi> and, <hi>Meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ùs eſt, innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem eſſe, in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino ignis, cum Filio. Dei, quàm in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>lo, ſine illo.</hi> Hierom <hi>in Epiſt. ad Euſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium. Ne in immenſum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumen exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam; quaere, &amp; inuenies, ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los Sanctos, aduerſa perpeſſos</hi> Chryſoſt, Homil. 4. in <hi>Philip:</hi> thus, <hi>Pro Chriſto pati, munus eſt, maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris admirationis, quàm mortuos excitare:</hi> In the one, I am a debtor to Chriſt; in the other Chriſt is a debtor to me. <hi>Anguſtin Ciuitat.</hi> 18.49, ſaith Chriſt by ſuffering <hi>Iudas,</hi> and vſing him well, gaue a patterne to the Church, of induring euil.—<hi>Paſſione oſtendit, quid ſuſtinere, proveritate, Reſurrectione, quid sperare, in aeternitate, debeamus. Ambroſe,</hi> calleth Patience, the Mother of the faithful. The Fathers haue wrote, whole tractates; <hi>Tertullian,</hi> a Booke <hi>de Patientia: Cyprian</hi> another Booke, <hi>de Bono patientiae.</hi>
                     </note> The Laſt Motiue, why you yeelded to their temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, might be, The conſideration of your preſent enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, your freedome from all Taxes, your worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8483:22"/>among them, and the diuerſe gifts, which, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, are vſually tendered to their new Proſelites, and their alluring Promiſes, the Baites of vnſtable Soules. What perchance they could not effect vpon you, by you, by dryed Bull-pizells, by knotted Ropes, tip't with black-and-blew; by Whippes diſcoloured with thy blood, by multiplyed blowes, fiercely inflicted on thy Belly, by yokes, by manicles and pedicles of iron; by vnwholſome vapoures; the cold dampes, and naſtineſſe of Dungeons in the night; by reproaches, hunger, thirſt, nakednes, ſcorching heates, labour, and torture in the day, (for, this is the miſuſage of poore Captiued-Chriſtians, by the barbarous tyranny of ſauage Mahumetans) I ſay, what thoſe Miſcreantes by ſuch extreamities could not compaſſe; the enticements of pleaſure, and worldly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, did worke about, on thee, to their deſires. The ſawning ſun-ſhine, might make you put of the habit of Chriſtianitie, which the ſtorme of Perfection, perhaps, made you keepe cloſe. Heere you ſhould haue remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the Apoſtolicall Thunder-bolt, vpon thoſe; that are <hi>Louers of pleaſure, more then louers of God,</hi> 2. Timoth, 3.4. <hi>From ſuch turne away</hi> or, the Example, of that choſen Veſſel of Honor, Galat. 6, 14. <hi>God forbid, that I ſhould glory, ſaue in the Croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, whereby the World, is crucified vnto me; and I vnto the World.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>n</hi> Other places againſt the delightes of this world, are 2. <hi>Peter,</hi> 2.18.—<hi>Rom.</hi> 12, 2. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5, 30. <hi>Iohn</hi> 6, 38. <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 2, 1.—<hi>Iob.</hi> 21.1. <hi>Luke</hi> 6, 25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13, 13. 1 <hi>Timoth,</hi> 5, 5. 1 <hi>Iohn,</hi> 2, 15. <hi>Matt.</hi> 49. <hi>Matt.</hi> 16, 24: <hi>fortaſſe, non eſt Laborioſum homini, relinquere ſua; ſed valde laborioſum eſt, relinquere ſemet ipſum: minus eſt, abnegare, quod habet; valdè multum eſt, abnegare, quod eſt.</hi> Gregory Homil. 32, in Euangel.</note> For, how can a Chriſtian be bettered then the world? when he is better then the World. Matt. 6.20. <hi>We muſt lay our our tre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſure, where Ruſt, Moth or Theiues,</hi> thinges ſenſeleſſe,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8483:23"/>ſenſitiue or reaſonable may not hurt. Our hearts muſt be ſet againſt the World; for, if it did loue vs, wee ſhould not loue it; but ſince it hateth Vs, let Vs hate it; <hi>and let our conuerſation be in Heauen;</hi> and let vs with the Apoſtle, Philip. 3.8. <hi>account all things but loſſe, all thinges but dung, that wee may win Chriſt:</hi> but you (poore ſoule) contrarily, by ſeeking to gaine the World, did looſe Chriſt. Falſe pleaſures, and ſeeming-gaine, with-drew you from Him, who is the Great, the Only Gaine. <hi>For, if you be Circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let me not be thought, (beloued in the Lord) to be too ſeuere, in aggrauating the Circumſtances, of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate Poenitents Sinne. I profeſſe, my heart is mooued with ſorrow, for him: and pitty, toward him: I grieue with him, who grieueth: I beare, part of his burden. And whil'ſt I ſtrike, I grone; whil'ſt I reprooue, my Bowels earne, and my faint Paſſions melt. But, which is better, a pleaſing, pleaſant neate Phyſitian, or an healing? <hi>Non quaero medicum elegantem, ſed ſanantem,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Wiſe-man</hi> of old. As I expect <hi>mercy,</hi> I would not adde weight to the oppreſſed, nor, breake, the <hi>bruized reede.</hi> But, <hi>ſince in my hearing, ſuch a Fault, was ſaid in effect, to be payde-for too deare, with ſuch a Pennance:</hi> ſince too many in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, out of a Compaſſion vncharitably-charitable, Leſſen ſuch an offence: ſince it is preſumed, that Diuerſe praeſent, haue runne the ſame courſe, with the delinquent (though it cannot be prooued as yet) and ſince it may turne to the terror of others hereafter (who of this Maritime-towne may be taken Captiues) I haue labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to cut-out the Core; to ſhew the Renouncing of Chriſt, to be a moſt heynous, abominable, and execrable ſinne. I acknowledge, We muſt not be too bitter
<note n="o" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sic neceſſe eſt, vulneratae ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae, medicamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>um temperetur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e miniâ me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>enti auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, ampliùs vulneretur. God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fridus Abbas Vindocinenſis, lib. Epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 12.</note> Salt-water is not ſo fit, to clenſe and whiten ſome things as the freſh, and ſomethings are better preſerued, with Sugar, then with Lalt. The good Shepheard, caſt not away, <hi>the loſt-ſheepe; but, laid it on his ſhoulders, reioycing,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8483:23"/>Luke</hi> 15.5. Yea, therefore dyed, that, it might not dye. When there was <hi>mors in ollâ,</hi> Meale was caſt in. 2. Kings, 4.41. <hi>An ouer-earneſt impetuous Reproofe, kills, inſteede of cutting</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ferrum de manubrio proſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit, cùm de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptione, ſermo durior excidit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregorius Magnus.</hi>
                     </note> Yet, the naughtie water and barren Ground were healed with Salt, by the meanes of the ſame <hi>Eliſha</hi> 2. <hi>Kings.</hi> 2.21. <hi>The good Samaritan,</hi> powred, as well <hi>Wine</hi> as <hi>Oile</hi> into the wound. <hi>Ferè dulcia omnia, in bilem, &amp; amaro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem commutantur. The Word of God is likened to Hony. Pſal.</hi> 19, 11. Yet Hony applyed to woundes, breedes ſmart, ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the beginning of <hi>Phocions</hi> Life <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; <hi>etiam mel habet ſatietatem.</hi> Therefore it is good, to widen the <hi>Orifice;</hi> and to ſearch the wound, to the bottom. <hi>Palliated</hi> Cures do breed more paine. Therefore that thy Shame before Men, may take of, the ſhame, which otherwiſe would be Great, before God, and all the Angels of Heauen, and all the bleſſed Saints at the Dreadfull Day of Retribution; and this thy preſent Humiliation, may finde acceptance with God, <hi>Condemne thy ſelfe, that thou may'ſt not be Condemned:</hi> The readieſt way to Heauen, is by acknowledging thy offence, to haue deſerued Hell. It will be a godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, breeding future Comfort, patiently, and willingly, to heare a Recapitulation of thy ſinnes. With <hi>Lots-wife</hi> thou haſt look't backe to <hi>Sodom.</hi> Thou haſt giuen cauſe of offence to many
<note n="q" place="margin">
                        <hi>Quod eſt proximi pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, eſt tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m peccatum; ſi tibi placet;</hi> much more, if he fell, through thy example. <hi>Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis exemplum oſtendentes, rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem animae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditae reddent,</hi> ſaith <hi>Diuine</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
                     </note> Thou conuerſed'ſt with <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Renegados,</hi> and they are able almoſt to corrupt a Saint: <hi>A little leauen, leaueneth the whole lumpe</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">
                        <hi>Citiùs, quae amara ſunt, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant dulcia, quàm quae dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia ſunt, amara. Naturâ ita com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratum eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard, vt cùm honum malo coniunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, non malum, à bono meliore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſed bonum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> malo contamine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
                     </note> The <hi>Leproſie</hi> infected the very ſtones, of the Leapers-houſe: and the infected ſtones, were to be carried away: yea, the vninfected ſtones, were to be ſcraped within, round-about <hi>Leuit.</hi> 14.41. Therefore haſt thou neede of <hi>much clenſing.</hi> Thou haſt changed, thy Habit and Veſtmentes, in token, of change in Religion: thou haſt denyed thy Faith. Thy ſinne of being <hi>Circumciſed,</hi> was a bloody ſinne; Thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of thy head, thy <hi>Crimen crinium,</hi> I will call, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, morally, in a double ſenſe <hi>Capitale.</hi> Thy fighting againſt Chriſtians, was an offence of an high-hand, lifted
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8483:24"/>vp againſt Chriſt. Thou wert ouer head and eares. Wholy vnder water; <hi>thou wert Totally falne; and if thou had'ſt then dyed, without Repentance, thou had'ſt beene as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely damned, as the Deuills of Hell.</hi> The preſent remorſe ſheweth, thou wert not Finally falne: thou haſt recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both thy Head aboue, and thy Body out of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which might haue ſwallowed thee vp. And now, continuing in the eſtate of Repentance, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes thou art as ſure to be ſaued, as the Angels of Heauen.</p>
                  <p>I ſhould ſinne againſt Chriſt, againſt this our weake Brother, for whom Chriſt dyed, if I left him in thoughts of Deſpaire, and annexed no Comfort: Therefore will I now come to the third, and laſt inference from my Text. That the preſent damnable eſtate, of them, that beleeue in Circumciſion, doth not hinder, but rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, the bleſſed eſtate of him who repenting after Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, deſireth to be receiued into the Body of Chriſts Church. I muſt be breefe. The ſumme is, <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> is of ſo great a power, that it tyeth Gods hands from puniſhing. The firſt hearty Grone of a truely Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, and fully poenitent ſoule, findeth <hi>Mercy</hi> with the God of Mercies, though thouſands cozen themſelues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell, by ſelfe preſuming, thinking they haue repented. Repentance waſheth away ſinnes, reconcileth and reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Vs vnto God, it purchaſeth Grace, it prepareth Vs for Glory: it is <hi>ſecunda tabùla poſt naufragium. If Caine, Achitophel, the Iewes who vrg'd our Sauiours death, if</hi> Iudas, <hi>if, He that ſinneth againſt the Holy-Ghoſt, of the Deuills them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues could ſufficiently Repent, and continue in it, I ſhould not doubt of their Saluation.</hi> That ſinne cannot be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, which cannot be pardoned through Repentance. Let not the bold, daring preſumptuous ſinner heare this <hi>Truth:</hi> I ſpeake to a <hi>Contrite Heart,</hi> to a <hi>Sorrowfull ſoule,</hi> a Conſcience, in agonie and anguiſh, to keepe it from Gulph of diſpaire. I cannot but adde, That innocency it ſelfe, giuen to <hi>Adam,</hi> was not ſo great a gift, as Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8483:24"/>which God vouchſafeth to vs;
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                        <hi>Aquinas</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. 2<hi>ae. Quaeſt.</hi> 106. <hi>Artic.</hi> 2. <hi>Donum Innocentiae, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundùm ſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideratum, eſt maius donum, quàm donum poenitentia; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, reſpectu Subiecti, eſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Beneficium.</hi> A whole, and perfect Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (to the eye of man) is better then the ſame in pecces and ſnippets; yet a Garment in peeces, may be ſo ſewed, and decked, and the ſeames ſo laced, with Gold, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich'd with Pearle, that, to the ſame mans ſight, it will ſeeme better, then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer intire Veſture: So, <hi>a Broken and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite Heart</hi> (diſ-reputed by men) if it be beautified with <hi>Teares</hi> as <hi>Pearles;</hi> and the Rentes ſewed, couered and embrodered with ſeuerall Graces, as withneedle worke, &amp; wrought-Gold, (which is the trimming of the Churches Rayment, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13.—) is more precious in the ſight of true iudging men, of Angels, and eſpecially of God himſelfe, then hee, that needeth no Repentance. Wherefore, let vs not fly, <hi>cum Adamo, ad late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras, ſedcum Petro ad lachrymas.</hi>
                     </note> for the eſtate of Innocency was conferred on him, who had no oppoſite diſpoſition, but Repentance is giuen to vs, who in our Naturals, and by our perſonall miſdeedes, deſerue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, (without the death of Chriſt) but wrath, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and hell.</p>
                  <p>No meruaile therefore, <hi>if the Angels doe reioyce more ouer one ſinner that repenteth, than ouer many righteous, that neede no Repentance;</hi> comparatiuely with others, or in their owne vnguided opinions. I proceede, by how much the offence is the greater, and the Repentance more viuid and vigorous, hearty and feruent; by ſo much the more is the ioy of Angels increaſed. Of Angels did I ſay? yea, of God himſelfe,
<note n="t" place="margin">
                        <hi>Jpſa Spiritus-Sancti ſubſtantia, quae eſt quicquid ipſe eſt, contriſtari non poteſt, cùm habeat aeternam at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> incommunicabilem beatitudinem: magiſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>, ſit ipſa aeterna &amp; incommutabilis beatitudo, Auguſtin. de Geneſi ad Litteram.</hi> 4.9. <hi>Deus</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>eſt &amp; imperturbabilis. Ambroſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues</hi> thus, <hi>Gaudet Spiritus Sanctus, ſaluti noſtrae; non ſibi, qui non indiget laetitiâ.</hi>
                     </note> in whom though there be no parts, nor paſſions properly; yet, ſince metaphorically, and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> He is ſaid to be <hi>iealous,</hi> and <hi>Angry,</hi> for our tranſgreſſions, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.42. <hi>My iealouſie ſhall depart from thee, and I will be quiet, and no more angry,</hi> and verſe 43. <hi>Thou haſt fretted me in all theſe things</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>contriſtabas me. They vexed his holy ſpirit, Eſa.</hi> 63.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>afflicted it. And, I am preſſed vnder you, as a Cart is preſſed that is full of ſheaues, Amos</hi> 2.13. And not onely Chriſt, as man, did weepe for Hieruſalem, (for his enemies in Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem) but, <hi>The holy ſpirit may be grieued,</hi> Epheſ. 4.30. <hi>Grieue not the holy Spirit of God, whereby ye are ſealed to the day of Redemption:</hi> He may be alſo ſaid, to reioyce in Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to delight in the Repentance of a ſinner. And if You, our deare afflicted Brother, bee now throughly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8483:25"/>ſorrowfull, for your enormous ſinnes, I dare ſay, <hi>There is ioy extraordinary, in heauen at this time, for thy ſake.</hi> I haue ſhewed, that Repentance remoueth away the Sword and the Fire from Paradiſe; that, it openeth the Gate of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. I had thought, at large to haue handled theſe points following.</p>
                  <p>That, no man is left wholly to himſelfe to be iudge of the degrees of his Repentance, and reconciliation with God; <hi>but in great perplexities, hath neede of the Keyes of the Church, committed to Gods Prieſts or Miniſters.</hi> Not the learned themſelues: (who would be partiall in their owne cauſes, though vpright Iudges of others) for euen the learnedſt, and beſt of theſe, haue ſome times called in for ayde of their fellow-Miniſters; much more, haue the halfe-learned, and the vnlearned, neede of counſaile, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, reprehenſion, of the ſpirituall foode of the Body and Bloud of our Lord; of Abſolution and Benediction mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall. That God hath giuen the guidance of ſoules to the Miniſters of the Church, <hi>who haue a true Miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Power, to remit Sinnes, and to inflict Poenitentiall Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. That Church-Diſcipline ought to be ſtrained vp higher, and, both in more vſe and more eſteems.</hi> That, the old iuſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerity of the Primitiue Church did, like an Indulgent Mother,
<note n="u" place="margin">Alijs animali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, intra ven trem, vbera in mammas deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt, mulieri ſupernè ad pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,: vt in promptu ſit, Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culari, Fouere, Nut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ire infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, quia parien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; alendi fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, Amor eſt, non Neceſſitas, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>utarch. Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus pater tam Pater, quàm Deus, Nulla mater tam Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quàm Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia.</note> Admit euen thoſe, that had more than once offended. That, Penance is not a cold, fruitleſſe, vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ceremony.
<note n="x" place="margin">
                        <hi>Auguſtine Homil.</hi> 49. <hi>inter Quinquaginta, alloquitur fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les adulteros,</hi> (not vs wee vſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ay, a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Drunkard, who ſets vp his reſt in drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) but, the Faithfull men that ſometime had beene A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers. <hi>Agite poeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, qualis agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Eccleſiá, vt pro vobis, oret Eccleſia. Nemo, ſibi dicat; Occultè ago: apud Deum ago, qui mihi ignoſcit, quia in corde ago. Ergo, fine cauſâ dictum eſt, Quaecun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſolueritis in Terra, ſoluta erunt in Coelis? Ergo ſine cauſâ, ſunt claues datae Eccleſiae Dei? Fruſtramus Euangelium? Fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dramus verba Chriſti?</hi> And in the laſt Homily of the fiftie, hee preferreth the Pardons of the Church, before the Pardons of Emperours: <hi>Certiores ſunt Claues Eccleſiae, quàm Corda Regum. Quibus clauibus quodcun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> in Terrâ ſoluitur, etiam in Coelo ſolutum promitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: &amp; multò eſt honeſtior humilitas, quâ, ſe quiſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> humiliat Eccleſiae Dei; &amp; labor minor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponitur, &amp; nullo temporalis mortis periculo, mors aeterna vitatur.</hi>
                     </note> Then, had I thought, to haue clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with earneſt exhortation to the Repentant, that, if hee knoweth any other ſinnes, or Circumſtances agrrauating his owne ſinnes, more than he hath reuealed, &amp; which doe trouble his conſcience, he would reueale them; and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8483:25"/>not thinke this puniſhment can couer or cure his offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, not knowne. And, that he would all the dayes of his life, labour to worke out his ſaluation, with feare and trembling, and in holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uties of Chriſtianity. <hi>Quis nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeabit ad Antidotum; qui hiauit ad Venenum?</hi> I would alſo haue beſought the Auditorie, not to triumph in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie of a Penitent; not to obiect hereafter, that offence vnto him, that God hath remitted, by his Church: but, rather to ſhew their charitie, their liberality in Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Captiues, in preuenting ſuch ſinnes; which is a worke, moſt acceptable to God. Laſtly, if any other of this company haue done any of the like offences, which yet lye hid. I would haue made it manifeſt vnto them, that they haue no remedy ſo good, as publike acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of their ſinnes, that they had need make their knees as hard as horne with kneeling; to cry and call to God till they grow hoarce; to weepe till their eyes bee bloud ſhot; to hunger and thirſt after mercy, to gape and gaſpeafter comfort: and when they haue done all theſe things, or the like deedes of mortification, they would be more willing than they are now, to humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to our Church, and by her abſolution, either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Pardon from God, or, (if it be before receiued) In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Grace Spirituall.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things, &amp; more, I propounded to haue handled: but I haue made a great treſpaſſe vpon the time already; and therefore conclude with Prayer vnto Almighty God.</p>
                  <trailer>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni Trino Deo Gloria.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8483:26"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8483:26"/>
                  <p>A RETVRNE FROM ARGIER.</p>
                  <p>A Sermon Preached at <hi>Minhead</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet</hi> the 16. of <hi>March,</hi> 1627. at the re-admiſſion of a relapſed Chriſtian into our CHVRCH.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Henry Byam</hi> Batchelar of Diuinity.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Reuel. 2. cap. pars 5. verſe.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and doe thy firſt workes.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.H.</hi> for <hi>I.P.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Thrale,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the Croſſe-Keyes, 1628.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8483:27"/>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:8483:27"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>REVEL. 2. cap. part 5. verſe.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Remember therefore from whence thou art fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and repent, and doe thy firſt workes.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall be forced to doe what Iſrael promiſed <hi>Sihon</hi> king of the Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21. paſſe through his country, without turning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide into the Fields or Vineyards: Or as your Saylors, whom time forbiddeth moſt while to draw Landskips, but with a Sea-marke or twaine, they make directly for the Harbour. He whoſe name is Wonderfull,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 9. Heb. 1.6.</note> and whom all the Angels of God muſt worſhip, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: Bids <hi>Iohn</hi> write in a Booke what he ſaw, and ſend it to the ſeuen Churches of <hi>Aſia, cap.</hi> 1: <hi>verſe</hi> 1. and here vnto the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> write, I paſſe by that ſtrange aſſertion of ſome men in fauour of vnwritten Traditions that tell vs the Apoſtles receiued commandement,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide Chemnit. exam. concil. Trident parte</hi> I<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. <hi>de Epiſtolit Apoſtolorum.</hi>
                     </note> not to Write, but onely to Preach: and yet S. <hi>Peter, Paul, Iames, Iude,</hi> write, and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> is bid Write, I muſt leaue on one ſide, the dignity of the Paſtors, and their duty on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and how what is written to the Churches, muſt bee ſent to the Paſtor of each Church;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Laudunenſ. in loc.</hi> Mal. 2.7.</note> either becauſe as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme</hi> will, their ſinnes, their ſoules ſhall be required at his hands; or becauſe the Prieſts lips ſhould preſerue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and they ſhould ſeeke the Law at his mouth. Yet
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8483:28"/>many, with another ſpirit then was his who ſpake it; ſay they are wiſer than their teachers; and for the Scriptures, <hi>praeſumunt, lacerant.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hieron. ad Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iuum. Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>v. vlt.</hi>
                     </note> O what ſenceleſſe ſence doe thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Ignorants oft times impoſe vpon it? But the wiſeſt will remember they are but Candleſtickes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they doe remember it, they are <hi>golden</hi> Candleſticks: but the Candles, the Starres themſelues which giue the light, are the Angels of the Churches, thoſe whom God hath ſingled out and ſet apart to teach his people.</p>
                  <p>The letter to the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> doth follow. <hi>I know thy workes, and thy labour, &amp;c.</hi> The firſt part whereof may be diuided into a proofe, and a reproofe. Firſt, what God approues and commends: ſecondly, what he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes and diſcommends. Many were their good workes, eſpecially their vndergoing the Croſſe and perſecution patiently. They made a difference betweene weakelings, and ſuch as offended preſumptuouſly; they could not forbeare them which were cuill. Though they were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to beare home the ſtraying ſheepe vpon their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.5.</note> yet the inceſtuous Corinthian muſt be cut off. Their Pulpit was not open to euery title-leſſe wandring Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, but his calling muſt be knowne, ere his doctrine muſt be heard, and therefore they did examine ſuch as came vnto them in the name of Apoſtles. And all this did they for the name of Chriſt: and what makes much for their commendation, they did all couragiouſly, they fainted not.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Gen. Homil.</hi> 30.</note> And yet after all this, comes in a <hi>neuertheleſſe,</hi> and they are reproued. <hi>Neuertheleſſe I haue ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, becauſe thou haſt left thy first loue. Chriſoſtome</hi> ſpeaking of the Phariſee in the 18. of S. <hi>Luke,</hi> that did pray ſo earneſtly, and faſt ſo ſtrictly, and pay tithes ſo conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably, and yet had a poore Publican preferred before him; tels vs that he ſuffered a ſtrange kinde of ſhipwrack. He had made a good voyage, and loſt all at home in his owne harbour: this can ſelfe-conceit doe. I may ſay as much of theſe Epheſians. They had made an excellent voyage, and were laden with many gracious commodities,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8483:28"/>and ſo one leake in the harbour did indanger all. This can the want of loue doe. <hi>Thou haſt left thy firſt loue. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and doe thy firſt workes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The parts are two
<list>
                        <item>1 <hi>An Exhortation,</hi> the firſt diſcouers the wound,</item>
                        <item>2 <hi>A Direction.</hi> the ſecond declares the remedy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </item>
                     </list>
Or here's
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Remember for the time paſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Repent for the time preſent,</hi> and</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Doe the firſt workes for the time to come.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
Or here's
<list>
                        <item>1 <hi>Their miſery or ſinne. They are fallen.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 <hi>The height or greatneſſe of their ſinne. Whence and whither they fell.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3 <hi>The ſalue, Repentance.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4 <hi>The Rowle which tyes it on, or the application. Doe thy firſt workes.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 S. <hi>Bernard</hi> hath a true ſaying; <hi>He that knoweth not his owne miſery, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vncapable of Gods mercy.</hi> And the Laodice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the next Cap. were in a wofull caſe, that ſaid, they were rich, and needed nothing, &amp; yet were wretched, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, poore, blind, naked. The firſt ſtep to repent, is to know our offence; and the way to ariſe, is to know our ſelues downe. The whole neede not a Phyſitian,
<note place="margin">Luk. 5.31. Rom. 3.23. cap. 3.2.</note> but they that are ſicke; and the ſin-ſicke Publican calls for mercy. Indeed we haue all ſinned as S. <hi>Paul</hi> tels vs: All in many things, as S. <hi>Iames.</hi> And though <hi>Noah</hi> were ſaid to bee a iuſt or vpright man, yet it was but <hi>inſua generatione,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the time wherein hee liued, and comparatiuely. And <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> were iuſt <hi>before God;</hi> that is, <hi>ſine fuce.</hi> What they did, they did vnfeinedly, and yet iuſt by the fauour of acceptation, not in the rigour of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. We may not therefore wonder that theſe Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans fell, and that their ſiluer was mixed with ſome droſſe, which could not indure the fire. Nor may we thinke their fall little, whom ſo ſeuere a Commination doth attend, as is the remouing of their Candleſticke out of his place.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:8483:29"/>
                  <p n="2">2 The ſinne laid to their charge, is the leauing of their firſt Loue.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ad Epheſ. cap.</hi> 1.15.16,</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> tels vs, that he ceaſed not to giue thankes to God for them, becauſe they had faith towards Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1 Reg. 7.21.</note> and loue towards all his Saints. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> tels vs, they were ſallen from this loue: their faith is not queſtioned, Theſe are the two pillars <hi>Iachin</hi> and <hi>Boas,</hi> which beare vp the entrance or porch into the Temple.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tortul. aduerſ. pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>inity.</note> Faith and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty muſt goe together, and muſt be <hi>numerus ſine diuiſione,</hi> diſtinguiſhed they may be, diuided, ſundred they cannot be, and be at all. And therefore it is not ſaid, They were fallen from loue,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>a in loc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>anch. tomo</hi> 7. <hi>de perſeuerant. Sanctorum.</hi>
                     </note> for ſo they muſt haue come within the compaſſe of S. <hi>Pauls Nothing,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. but they were fallen from their <hi>firſt loue, à tanto gradu,</hi> from that feruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which formerly they had. Either they loued not <hi>all</hi> the Saints, or they loued them not in that meaſure: they were partiall, or they were cold in their affections.</p>
                  <p>This is that ſinne which called for ſo heauy a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and without Repentance and Returning to their firſt eſtate, would (notwithſtanding their many other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious actions) bring on them an euerlaſting miſery. And yet doe we ſcarce loue any Saints much leſſe all; and we neuer did eſteeme that doctrine which teacheth vs to looſe our purſe-ſtrings, and powre out. Wee haue fed our Auditory ſo long with <hi>Sola fides,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Cap.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Ambroſe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Hip. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Pap.</hi>
                     </note> that Charity is frozen amidſt the fire of our zeale, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> is diſmiſſed with that cold, comfortleſſe almes in S. <hi>Iames, Depart in peace.</hi> And moſt of vs are become <hi>Cuſtodes non Domini,</hi> ſlaues to god Mammon; we haue not power of our owne. And if any be ſo tender hearted, as to relieue, reſtore, compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate his brothers miſery; ſome ſhall vntruely iudge him for no true Chriſtian; and other new reformers ſhall neere challenge him of <hi>old</hi> Religion. Thus dare preſumptuous impiety fall not onely from her firſt loue, if ſhe had euer any,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s. 7.8. Pro. 5.22.</note> but from loue it ſelfe, and yet ſhall challenge heauen for her inheritance. She ſhall adde ſinne to ſinne, and bind many together, and yet forget her ſelfe to be holden with the cords of her owne ſinne. Shee ſhall fall, neuer any
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8483:29"/>Epheſian worſe, few euer like, and yet perſwade her ſelfe ſhe ſtands vpright.</p>
                  <p>The Church of Epheſus is onely taxed for defect in Ioue, but many of vs are like <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> lame in both fecte. We are <hi>fallen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 9.13.</note> we are fallen not onely from loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward all the Saints,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.33.</note> 
                     <hi>but from the faith we had in the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> Perſecuion can ſeperate vs from the loue of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.16.</note> and the blaſt of affliction can make vs throw off the ſhield of faith. Yea, many times we fall away <hi>non perſecutionis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuſed voluntario lapſu,</hi> the demand of a doore-keeper, or the voice of a Maide, will terrifie vs, as it befell <hi>Peter;</hi> and we are prone vpon the leaſt occaſion to renounce, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.10.11.</note> defie that excellent Name by which wee haue <hi>hope,</hi> the bleſſed name of <hi>Ieſus.</hi> A name which euery tongue muſt confeſſe, to which euery knee muſt bow, then which there is no other name vnder heauen where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we muſt be ſaued;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cic. in Verrem. lib.</hi> 2. of <hi>Sotor.</hi>
                     </note> and of which a Heathen could giue this teſtimony, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t vno verbo exprimi non poſſit.</hi> It is a name of wonder.</p>
                  <p>But ſome haue thought it tollerable,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertul. apol. c.</hi> 27.</note> if not lawfull in time of peſecution to deny <hi>Manente apud animum propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to:</hi> ſo the minde be free. Indeed what haue not ſome thought, or what monſtrous opinions were there euer heard of, but could finde ſome one or other to defend them? One commends the quartan Ague, another writes in praiſe of Folly; <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> thinkes the ſnow is black,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Danaeus in cap.</hi> 4 <hi>Aug. de Hereſ. Gab. Prateolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> and <hi>Catilina ſi iudicatum erit meridie non lucere certus erit competitor.</hi> He will ſweare the ſunne ſhines not at noone day. The Baſilidians, the Dauid-Georgians, not onely defend that damnable opinion of denying, but (ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly doth one abſurditie, one ſinne beget another) they ſcoffed at, they ſcorned, they cryed ſhame on all the holy Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yrs for their ſufferings. But we haue not ſo learn'd Chriſt. Thoſe Chameleons liue not in our Element, nor come they within the verge of the Church. <hi>Omnis Ariſtip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum decuit color.</hi> He is none of ours. No no: the reſolued Chriſtian will ſcorne to bow his knee to <hi>Baal.</hi> He knowes
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8483:30"/>there is a woe to him that hath a double heart,
<note place="margin">Ecclus. 2.</note> and is faint-hearted. He knowes we may not take the name of God in vaine,
<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> much leſſe deny him. And that wee muſt not feare thoſe which kill the body, and are not able to kill the ſoule: but rather feare him which is able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both ſoule and body in hell: and that whoſoeuer ſhall deny his Sauiour before men, ſhall one day be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before God.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Thom. Aquin.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. 2<hi>ae. q.</hi> 3. <hi>art.</hi> 2. Math. 10.23. B. <hi>King,</hi> on <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> Lect. 29.</note> This makes the Schooleman reſolue, that vpon paine of damnation, we are bound in ſome caſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to abide the triall, and confeſſe our faith, when it ſhall conduce either to the honour of God, or the profit of our neighbour. And that indulgence of our bleſſed Sauiour, of flying from City to City, is neither for all men, nor all times. This made the Saints, the ſeruants of God, not onely not deny, but to proclaime themſelues Chriſtians, and to run vpon thoſe vnſufferable torments and iawes of death,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. 2ae. <hi>q.</hi> 124. <hi>art.</hi> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>ex zelo fidei &amp; charitate fraterna, &amp;c,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquinas.</hi> Out of the feruency of their faith, and to hearten and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage their Brethren. The Martyrs haue often come forth and offered themſelues to the fire, or other furie of their enemies.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apolog. cap.</hi> 1.</note> This made <hi>Tertullian</hi> cry out, <hi>Chriſtianis quid ſimile? &amp;c.</hi> What may be compared to the Chriſtian? queſtion him, and he is glad: accuſe him, and he ſaith guilty:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Euſeb. Eccleſ. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> adiudge him to death, and he will giue thee thankes. This made <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi> giue a liberall teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them in his time, It is their deſire in Gods quarrell rather to dye than to liue.</p>
                  <p>Not to ſpeake of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> cut in twaine,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sixtus Senenſis lib. Sanct. lib.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſtoned, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> beheaded, <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Denne, and his three companions in the Ouen: and indeed which of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets haue not beene perſecuted and ſlaine?
<note place="margin">Act. 7.52. 2 Machab. 6. ibid. c. 7.</note> nor of <hi>Elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> beaten to death being foureſcore yeere old and ten? nor of that honourable woman, and her ſeuen ſonnes, enduring to the amazement of the tormentors. And though it be moſt true as one ſaith,
<note place="margin">Eraſmus virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; Martyr. comparat.</note> 
                     <hi>Parentes atrocius tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentur in liberis quàm in ſeipſis.</hi> The poore Mother ſuffered more Martyrdomes, than ſhee had children, and euery
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:8483:30"/>ſtripe their backes felt, went to her heart, yet ſhe exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted euery one of them, with a manly ſtomacke, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all to dye couragiouſly, neuer deploring that ſhe had brought them forth to ſuch miſery, but ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed that ſhe ſhould be the mother of ſo many Saints.</p>
                  <p>And though I know it to be true what the Orator hath <hi>vetera exempla profictis fabulis iam audiri.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cic.</hi> 3. <hi>in verrem.</hi>
                     </note> Yet will I touch at a few of thoſe holy Saints and bleſſed Soules in Heauen Who willingly, ioyfully, conſtantly yeelded vp their ſpirits in his quarrell, who firſt trod out the way,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Euſeb. Eccleſ. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and ſhed his blood for them. <hi>Policarpe,</hi> When many vrged him to deny his Sauiour and ſaue himſelfe, anſwered re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutly, foureſcore and ſix yeeres haue I ſerued <hi>him,</hi> neither hath he euer offended me in any thing, and how can I reuile my king who hath thus long preſerued me? And when the <hi>Proconſul</hi> threatned to burne him, his anſwere was; Thou threatneſt fire for an hower, which laſteth a while and is quickly quenched, but thou art ignorant of the euerlaſting fire, of the day of Iudgment, and of the endleſſe torments which are prepared for the wicked. And being now come to his laſt, he turneth from his perſecutor to his Maker. O God (ſaith he) I thanke thee, that thou haſt graciouſly vouchſafed this day and this houre,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Idem lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 32. <hi>Gr.</hi> 35.</note> to alot me a portion among the number of Martyrs and ſeruants of Chriſt. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> when he was ſent from <hi>Syria</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> to be meat for wild beaſts. Now (ſaith he) doe I begin to be a Diſciple, I weigh neither viſible nor inviſible things: Let fire, Gallowes, Violence of beaſts, bruiſing of bones, racking of the members, ſtamping of my whole body, and all the plagues Satan can inuent light vpon me, ſo I may win my Sauiour Chriſt. <hi>Simeon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fox</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
                        <hi>perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one. Euſeb. Eccleſ. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> being an hundred and twenty yeeres old, was ſcourged many daies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and at laſt crucified. <hi>Peter</hi> a Noble man of <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>media,</hi> had his body rent in pieces with the laſh, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, vinegar mixt with ſalt, was powred into his wounds, and laſt of all he was fryed to death vpon a Grediron.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:8483:31"/>
                     <hi>Sanctus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Idem lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> one that would neither confeſſe his name, kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, or country, but onely that he was a Chriſtian, had his body fired, ſeared, ſcorched with hot plates of braſſe. Forty Martyrs,
<note place="margin">Fox indecima perſecut. ex Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil.</note> yong Gentlemen, for profeſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Chriſtians, were in the depth of winter compelled to ſtand in a Pond all the night, and in the morning, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out and burned. Take one Woman among the reſt, <hi>Blandina,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 5 <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> who was tormented from morning till night; the executioners tormenting her by turnes, and after a world of cruelties, ſhe was wrapped in a net, and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled before a wilde Bull, which toſſed her too and fro vpon his hornes; and for a farewell, ſhe had her head di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided from her body.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iaques de La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uardin Hiſt</hi>-of <hi>Scanderbeg. lib.</hi> 11.</note> I haue read of ſome, and thoſe ſome of the valianteſt the world did ſee within their age, who, after all kinde of ignominy and Turkiſh crueltie practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon them, were fleaed aliue by little and little, for fifteene dayes together.
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.32. <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 40 <hi>Gr.</hi> 41. <hi>Ibid. cap.</hi> 41. <hi>Gr.</hi> 42. <hi>Jbid. cap.</hi> 40. <hi>Idem. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> And (to borrow the Apoſtles words,) what ſhall I more ſay? for the time would be too ſhort for me to tell how ſome had their eyes pricked out with ſharpe quilles, as <hi>Metras:</hi> ſome were beaten to death with cudgels, as <hi>Iſchyrion:</hi> ſome had all their teeth beaten out of their head, as <hi>Apollonia.</hi> And what ſhould I ſpeake of the ſetting them in the ſtockes, and ſtretching their legges vnto the fifth hole?
<note place="margin">Fox decima perſecut.</note> or of the iron chayre, wherein they ſate broyling to death? of holes made in their neckes, and their tongues drawne out backward? their eyes pulled out, and the hollow places ſeared with hot irons?
<note n="a" place="margin">D. <hi>King</hi> on <hi>Jonas,</hi> Lect. 24.</note> powning in mortars? rowling in barrels ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with pikes of iron?
<note n="b" place="margin">D. <hi>Benefield</hi> on <hi>Amos,</hi> Lect. 7</note> Womens breaſts ſeard?
<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Gab. Proteo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus lib.</hi> 7. § 7.</note> Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins faces whipped? their whole body abuſed, proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and tormented? I am faint in telling, and you bee weary in hearing, but they vnterrified, vndaunted, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all couragiouſly.
<note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eraſmus vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginum &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. comparat. Tertul. apol. c.</hi> 50. <hi>Hemming in</hi> Pſal. 84. verſ. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Tyrannornm ingenioſa crudelitas,</hi> ſaith one. The bloudy Tyrants ſet their wits on work to inuent torment; but <hi>nihil proficit exquiſitior quae<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>,</hi> ſaith ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the more the torments, the more the Martyrs. Their bloud was like corne ſowne, one brought forth many.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8483:31"/>Yea the perſecutors themſelues were aſtoniſhed to ſee their conſtancy, and how they went to their Martyrdom,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Naſians: Orat.</hi> 32 <hi>de Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baeis.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>tanquam ad epulas, tanquam ad delicias,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoſius Confeſſ. fidei cap</hi> 6 8. <hi>Naſians: Cyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neorum Carm. lib. &amp; Orat.</hi> 32. <hi>de Machabaeis.</hi> Heb. 12. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Maximus &amp;c.</hi> 26. <hi>Epiſt. inter opera Cypriani.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>tanquam ad nuptia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem thalamum,</hi> they went to the fire as to a feaſt, as to a dainty feaſt, as to their bridall bed.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore let vs alſo ſeeing that we are compaſſed with ſo great a cloud of witneſſes, caſt away euery thing that preſſeth down, and the ſinne that hangeth ſo faſt on. Let vs remember from whence we are fallen, that ſo wee may repent, and doe the firſt workes. We can offer vp no greater Sacrifice to our Maſter: We can purchaſe no greater happineſſe to our ſelues: We can leaue no better example to others: We can bring no greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to our friends, then vnder the hand of the mercileſſe Executioner vndauntedly to acknowledge whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants we are, and with a free, though fading ſpirit to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our Sauiour.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, We can offer vp no greater ſacrifice to our Maſter:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cypri. epiſt.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp; Epiſt.</hi> 25. <hi>&amp;c. Lib. de Duplici Martyrio inter opera Cypriani tomo.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note> You ſhall firſt vnderſtand who ought properly to be called a Martyr. <hi>Cyprian</hi> makes two ſorts. The firſt of them who ſhed their bloud, the ſecond of them who are ready ſo to do for Chriſts ſake: And to thoſe laſt torments were wanting (ſaith one) they were not wanting to the torments.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zacnh. tomo.</hi> 6. <hi>in cap.</hi> 2 <hi>ad Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip. verſ.</hi> 30. <hi>apud Aquinam.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. 2<hi>ae. q.</hi> 124. <hi>art.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Zanchius</hi> acknowledgeth that the Church did vſually call this later ſort Confeſſors, yet he will haue <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> a Martyr, and <hi>Hierom</hi> doth ſome where call the bleſſed Virgin a Martyr, <hi>quamuis in pace vitam finierit,</hi> &amp; <hi>Policrates</hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">
                        <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 28. <hi>G.</hi> 3.</note> calls <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt a Martyr. And <hi>Chriſoſt.</hi> tells the people of <hi>Antioch,</hi> that a man may alway be a Martyr, for <hi>Iob</hi> was one and ſuffered more then many Martyrs did,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Homil.</hi> 25.</note> ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi> in his Sermon of <hi>Abbot Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> pretily differenceth Martyrs from Confeſſors and ſomwhere elſe tells vs of three kinds of Martyrdom with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bloud. We muſt firſt conclude with <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> The cauſe, not the ſufferinge, makes a Martyr.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>in ſenten. Gab. Prateolus. Elench Heres lib.</hi> 3. §. 5.</note> We diſclaime the <hi>Campates</hi> a kind of <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> who would haue all voluntary Deaths Martyrdomes. I thinke
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8483:32"/>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calls them <hi>Circumcelliones.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Auguſt. de Haeres: cap.</hi> 69. <hi>Prateol. lib.</hi> 13. §. 16. <hi>Zanch. tomo.</hi> 6. <hi>in epiſt. ad Phil. Cap</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Idem ibid. Auguſt. tomo.</hi> 8. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 118. <hi>Vbi Supra. in Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 30. <hi>in</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">am</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">ae</hi>. <hi>q.</hi> 124. <hi>art:</hi> 4. <hi>Apud Zanch. vbi Supra. in cap.</hi> 1.</note> And likewiſe <hi>Peli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bianus</hi> who taught them to be Martyrs who ſlew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in deteſtation of their ſinnes. But ſo (ſaith one) <hi>Iudas</hi> ſhould haue been a Martyr. Secondly as <hi>Talis Cauſa</hi> ſo <hi>talis paena.</hi> They are Martyrs who teſtifie the truth <hi>Vſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>ad mortem,</hi> euen ſealing it with their bloud. The other whom the Church calls Confeſſors, are <hi>Perinde ac Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres, aequiuocè Martyres,</hi> ſo <hi>Zanchius: deſignati Martyres,</hi> ſo <hi>Tertullian interpretatiuè, inchoatiuè ſecundum quid, &amp; mentall Martyrs,</hi> So <hi>Caietan.</hi> And therfore we may be bold with S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to blot out ſome, and queſtion other ſome euen the holy innocents themſelues, queſtion I ſay not their bliſſe, <hi>but their teſtimony that the dignity of proto-martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> may remaine vnto S. <hi>Steuen.</hi> The ſumme of all is this. He is properly a Martyr, who is tormented to the death for the word of God,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.9.</note> &amp; for the teſtimony of Ieſus Chriſt. Of King <hi>Henry</hi> and Queene <hi>Mary</hi> Martyrs, both for the honor of the dead, and the peace of the Church, I ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.
<note place="margin">Academ. quaeſt.</note> Perchance the queſtion then was, or moſt while was for <hi>bounds</hi> as <hi>Tully</hi> ſpeakes, but now 'tis for the whole poſſeſſion and inheritance.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cic</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Officio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
                     </note> Nay 'tis <hi>vter eſſet non vter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraret.</hi> I am ſure Heauen cannot hold vs and Mahomet, and bleſſed is he that ſhall lay downe his life in ſo good a cauſe.
<note place="margin">Math. 10.42.</note> 
                     <hi>A Cup of cold water ſhall not looſe his reward. Whoſoeuer ſhall forſake Houſes,
<note place="margin">Mark. 10.30.</note> or Brethren or Siſters, or Father or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or Wife or Children, or Lands for the Name of Chriſt, ſhall receiue an hundred fold more for the preſent, and in the world to come eternall life.</hi> What ſhall he haue that forſaketh all? <hi>He that offereth praiſe and thankeſgiuing honoureth God.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50. verſ. vlt.</note> He that giues his bread to the poore members of Chriſt, feedes his Sauiour, But he that giues himſelfe, his life, his bloud, doth giue all, and therefore more then all. He that giues his life can giue no more,</hi> Iohn 15.13. <hi>Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen: thou couldſt offer no greater ſacrifice to thy Maſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, We can purchaſe no greater happineſſe to our ſelues. I ſhould much wronge you if I ſhould labour
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8483:32"/>to proue this. If heauen be better than earth; if the Crowne of life, better than the paines of death: if things eternall, better than temporall: if to be alwaies happy, better than euer in hazard, in feare, in trouble, then hee that ſuffereth for the name of Chriſt, doth to himſelfe purchaſe name, fame, heauen, happineſſe; and with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> hath choſen the better part, which ſhall neuer be taken from him: then he that loſeth his life ſhall finde it, <hi>Math.</hi> 10.39. and he that dyes with Chriſt, ſhall liue with him, ſhall raigne with him, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11. and the momentany afflictions which he doth here endure, ſhall cauſe to him <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a more excellent weight of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. In a word,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>p Chryſolog. ſerm.</hi> 40. <hi>Caluin inſtitut. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. § 7.</note> 
                     <hi>participes paſſionis</hi> ſhall be <hi>gloriae participes</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Chryſologus</hi>) If we ſhare with him in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction here, he will impart to vs bleſſedneſſe hereafter. So happy are theſe men whom God vouchſafeth that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall honour as to dye for him. Write them bleſſed, as the voice ſaid, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.13. no men more, no men like. <hi>And therefore remember from whence thou art fallen.</hi> Thou couldeſt purchaſe no greater happineſſe to thy ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, we can leaue no better example to others. S. <hi>Paul, Philip.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 12.14. tels vs that his durance turned to the furtherance of the Goſpell, inſomuch that many bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the Lord were emboldned through his bands, and durſt more frankely ſpeake the word. In Eccleſiaſtick Hiſtory you ſhall reade continually, how one Martyr led the way to another, and the noble reſolution they ſhewed in their death, made hundreds then aliue to take the ſame courſe: yea ſo powerfull is example in this kinde; that the very heathen not onely gaue them teſtimony of courage, but were won to the faith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Beda Hiſtory Angl. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Palatina,</hi> &amp; the 3. Conuerſ. of <hi>England, parte</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">a</hi>.</note> and ſealed the ſame toſtimony with their bloud. So did S. <hi>Alban</hi> beget his heads man to the faith, and had him his companion to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. So did the conſtancy of Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the ſecond, ſtrengthen S. <hi>Laurence;</hi> and S. <hi>Laurence</hi> brings <hi>Romanus</hi> from a perſecuting Souldier to bee his fellow Martyr. <hi>Tryphon</hi> did the like, and almoſt who did not?
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8483:33"/>The Phaenix aſhes (ſome ſay) yeelds another Phaenix: but the Martyrs by life and death begat many. <hi>Semen eſt ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis chriſtianorum.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertul. apolog. c.</hi> 50.</note> Now if they that turne many to righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, ſhall ſhine as the ſtars for euer and euer, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. How happy are thoſe faithfull witneſſes in heauen, whoſe holy liues, and vnterrified, vnappalled deaths did ſtrengthen ſome, and raiſe vp others, and draw thouſands from the very ſinke of Atheiſme and infidelity, to know and acknowledge their moſt gracious Redeemer? And therefore remember from whence thou art fallen, thou couldeſt neuer leaue a better example to others.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 And laſt of all, we can neuer bring greater comfort to our friends. The Heathen when his childe was dead, comforted himſelfe with that inexorable, vnauoidable law of mortality, <hi>ſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> me genuiſſe mortalem:</hi> but what vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able comfort would it be, to ſay, I know I haue begat one who is now a Saint in heauen? This made thoſe three Mothers,
<note place="margin">3 Conuerſ. of <hi>England, parte</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. <hi>Chryſolog. ſerm.</hi> 134. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Felicitas, Simphoroſa,</hi> and that other in the <hi>Machabees,</hi> to encourage <hi>each of them their ſeuen children</hi> in their torments; and the comfort they receiued in their childrens conſtancy, was much more than the pains they endured through the Tyrants furie. This made the Mother of <hi>Simphorianus</hi> run after him when he went to his Martyrdome, ſtill crying out, <hi>ſonne, ſonne, be mindfull of euerlaſting life, looke vp to heauen, &amp;c.</hi> And this made that women in <hi>Theodoret,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiſtor. Eccleſ. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 16.</note> renowned for her care, as well as conſtancy. When <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour had threatned death to all vn-arrianized Chriſtians at <hi>Edeſſa;</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtus</hi> the Gouernour with his Souldiers, ſtood ready in the Market place to execute the decree; A woman leading her little childe by the arme, broke through the preſſe, and laboured to get in among her fellowes. The Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour demanded her, whether ſhe went: ſhee tels him, ſhee would drinke of the ſame cup the reſt did. And being fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demanded what her childe made there, and why ſhe had brought it, her anſwer was, That he alſo might dye that bleſſed death. Indeed great was the ioy of the whole
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8483:33"/>Church,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eraſmus virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; Martyr. Comparat. &amp; Cyprianus de. lapſis: tomo</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>vbi Martyr conſtanter exhalaſſet animam pro Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto.</hi> Great was their ioy, if any dyed couragiouſly; and great their ſorrow, their griefe, if any fainted cowardly, wretchedly, wickedly. <hi>Remember therefore from whence thau art fallen:</hi> Thou couldeſt bring no greater comfort to thy friends.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> writing to the impriſoned Chriſtians,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.</note> whom he cals Martyrs, exhorts them to endure conſtantly by the example of <hi>Lucretia, Mutius, Empedocles,</hi> and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who ſuffered much, to little purpoſe, onely to get a terrene fading fame among men. <hi>Tanti vitrum?
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> quanti ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum margaritum?</hi> If they did ſo much for glaſſe, what ſhould we doe for gold? if honour were bought at ſo deare a rate, why ſhould we grudge vpon the ſame tearmes to get heauen? <hi>Nazianzene</hi> ſome where tels vs,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cygneorum Carm. lib. pag.</hi> 1051. <hi>a.</hi>
                     </note> that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then were onely valiant, when the danger could not bee ſhunned, it was much if it were ſo. But what bad <hi>Scaeuola</hi> burne his right hand for miſſing in the murder of <hi>Porſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na?</hi> or if he ſtood in danger, what is that to <hi>Lucrecia?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cic. orat. de Proùinc. Conſul.</note> or to thoſe noble Virgins, who threw themſelues head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into Wels to ſaue their Virginity? Who made <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> and <hi>Torquatus</hi> kill their ſonnes? Who compelled <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus</hi> to returne <hi>ad crudeliſſimum hoſtem,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cic.</hi> 3. <hi>officiorum</hi>
                        </note> ad exquiſita ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicia,</hi> to thoſe mercileſſe enemies, to that ſtrange death of his at <hi>Carthage.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">B. <hi>King,</hi> on <hi>Ionas</hi> Lect. 27.</note> And what made the Stoickes ſo prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall of their liues, that they little regarded the very extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of tortures? and when they were vpon the racke, they would cry out, <hi>O quàm ſuaue!</hi> as if it were ſport? Surely nothing but a thing of nothing. Honour, and a name amongſt men, while the noble Martyr ſhall haue the acclamation of the Angels, and an <hi>euge</hi> of his Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. Heauen is his; and as <hi>Nathan</hi> told <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> if that be too little, he ſhall haue more; <hi>his name ſhall neuer periſh from the earth.</hi> As <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid of <hi>Metellus,
<note place="margin">Pro domo ſua ad pontifices.</note> Calamity hath made them immortall, euen here alſo.</hi> Their priſons were vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited as places made holy by the inhabitants. Men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, young, old, did kiſſe the chaines, in which they had
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8483:34"/>beene fettered: preſerue the ſwords for Reliques by which any had beene depriued of their life: their aſhes ſacred: their memories bleſſed: their anniuerſaries kept, the day of their death being their <hi>natalitiae,</hi> the firſt of time in which they began truely to liue. And what could be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, where Myracles were plentifull? God euen at thoſe very places where the Martyrs lay witneſſing their bleſſed ſtate by many miracles: but I forbeare. As S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaid of one of them,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De virginibus lib.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Appellabo Martyrem &amp; praedicauiſatis.</hi> The name of a Martyr is a whole world of commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and doe thy firſt workes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But this is not all, here is a <hi>Quo vadis;</hi> here is, a whither we fall,
<note place="margin">Cap. 2. verſ. 13.</note> as well as whence we fall; and a <hi>Terminus ad quem.</hi> As God ſaid by <hi>Ieremy, The people haue committed two euils, They hue forſaken me,
<note place="margin">1 San. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.8.</note> the fountaine of liuing waters, and haue digged them pits, euen broken pits that can hold no water;</hi> and as elſewhere: <hi>They haue forſaken me, and worſhipped other gods, no gods; They haue gone from Chriſt, to Antichriſt; from God to Mahomet,</hi> that ſame <hi>inimicus homo,</hi> that hath done ſo much miſchiefe to Gods vineyard.
<note place="margin">Iohn 19.</note> Wherefore as <hi>Pilate</hi> ſometime ſaid of him, in whom he confeſſed, <hi>that he could finde no fault at all: Ecce homo.</hi> I ſhall ſay to you of this curſed Caitiffe, and ſcourge of Chriſtendome, in whom I can finde nothing but faults,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prateolus ex Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coldo Haereſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>in Bayras Polidor Virgil de inuent. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> and thoſe monſtrous ones. <hi>Ecce homo,</hi> take a view of him. And though I cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, whether he were <hi>genere admodum vilis,</hi> as ſome: or <hi>nobili genere natus,</hi> as others: Whether he were deſcended of Noble, or obſcure Anceſtors: nor whether his Parents were Iewiſh or Pagan, or both, or neither: nor whether he were an <hi>Arabian,</hi> or a <hi>Perſian,</hi> or neither: nor whether he was buried at <hi>Mecha,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Purchas. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> or <hi>Medina,</hi> or at neither, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured of dogges (the helliſh hiſtory of his life and death being as obſcure as hell:) yet all accord that he was what <hi>Tully</hi> ſaid of one,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jn Verrem.</hi> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Immenſa aliqua vorago aut gurges vitiorum turpitudinum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> omnium,</hi> the very puddle and ſinke of ſin and wickedneſſe. A thiefe, a murderer, and adulterer, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8483:34"/>a Wittall. And from ſuch a diſſolute life proceeded thoſe licentious lawes of his.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ph. Morney de veritate Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an relig. c.</hi> 33.</note> That his followers may auenge themſelues as much as they liſt. That he that kils moſt Infidels, ſhall haue the beſt roome in Paradiſe: and hee that fighteth not luſtily, ſhall be damned in hell. That they may take as many Wiues as they be able to keepe. And leſt inſatiable luſt might want whereon to feed, to ſurfet, he alloweth diuorce vpon euery light occaſion. He himſelf had but eleuen Wiues, beſides Whores;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Purchas lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. § 5. <hi>Ant. Gueuarra. epiſt. ad Comitem Myrand.</hi>
                     </note> but the Grand-Signior in our daies kept three thouſand Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines for his luſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Licurgus,</hi> his lawes allowed Man-ſlaughter: <hi>Phoroneus</hi> permitteth Theft: <hi>Solon Solinus</hi> tolerateth Adultery: <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Pompilius</hi> makes it lawfull to conquer and keepe: The Lydians and Baleares ſuffer, nay, command what I ſhame to ſpeake: And euen he whom we muſt acknowledge the firſt and greateſt Law-giuer vnder God; <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelfe will ſuffer ſomething <hi>propter duritiem cordis:</hi> but take all the worſt out of all theſe, and out of all other the worſt of all;
<note place="margin">1 Reg. 12.10.</note> and <hi>Rehoboams</hi> little finger ſhall be bigger than his fathers loines. The wickedneſſe which <hi>Mahomets</hi> lawes alone maintaine, are more and more monſtrous then them all.</p>
                  <p>Not to tell you of the Angell hee met ten thouſand times huger than the whole world:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hemming. lin Pſal.</hi> 84. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> nor of thoſe Angels that luſted, now hanged in iron chaines till the day of iudgement: nor of their faire Hoſteſſe taken vp into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and made the beautifull day-ſtarre. Nor of <hi>Seraphiel</hi> his Trumpet, which is as long as a lourney of fifty yeeres,
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Purchas lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> ſome ſay, fiue hundred: and that is more ſutable to ſome of his relations, as namely of an Oxe ſo huge, that it is a thouſand yeeres iourney from one of his hornes to the other; and of a Key ſeuen thouſand miles long (the doores themſelues muſt needs be great) and of the Bridge that is made ouer hell; and of the reſurrection of Birds and Beaſts: and how death ſhall be changed into a R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mme; and what that Atheiſt. <hi>Agrippa</hi> ſaid for the Aſſe, this
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8483:35"/>damned circumciſed miſcreant dare ſay for his Ram and that the Ram,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cornelius Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa de vanitat. ſcient. Purchas. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> (more charitable then his Maſters) doth pray for his perſecutors, for thoſe which ſacrifice him. I ſhould be loath once to mention thoſe whet-ſtone lyes of his, but that you may ſee what a iolly fellow thoſe men ſerue which fall away and turne <hi>Turke.</hi> And therefore let it not diſtaſt if I adde, How <hi>Hali</hi> his ſword would cut Rocks aſunder, (but you muſt vnderſtand 'twas an hundred Cubitts long) How Mahomet found the Sunne where it lay reſting it ſelfe in a yeallow fountaine. How the Moone brake in two peeces, and fell vpon the Hills of <hi>Mecha,</hi> but Mahomet made it whole againe. How he tells of an <hi>Vtopian</hi> land white as milke, ſweete as Muske, ſoft as Saffron, and bright as the Moone: yet this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to his Paradiſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hemming. in Pſal.</hi> 84. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> the ground thereof is gould watered with ſtreames of Milke, Hony and Wine. How there his followers after the day of Iudgement, ſhall haue a merry madd world,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Purchas. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> and ſhall neuer make an end of eating, drinking, and <hi>colling wenches.</hi> And theſe (if you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it) are ſweete Creatures indeed; for if one of them ſhould ſpet into the Sea, all the waters thereof would become ſweete.</p>
                  <p>This is a taſt of his infernall doctrine, of thoſe ſtrange lyes and ſtrong deluſions with which he hath bewitched the world, and led men-hood-wink't into the Abiſſe of perdition.</p>
                  <p>This is,
<note place="margin">So <hi>Denis</hi> in his Treatiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Mahomet</hi> Printed at <hi>London.</hi> 1531. <hi>Whittaker</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Campian.</hi> in his anſwer to the tenth reaſon.</note> or is like that Dragons tayle. Revel. 12.4. <hi>Which drew the third part of the Starres of Heauen and caſt them to the earth,</hi> this is that ſame <hi>Abaddon</hi> and man of ſinne. This is <hi>Mahomet,</hi> one that hath brought more ſoules to Hell, then all other ſects and heretikes beſides. I take that ſaying of a Reuerent Diuine, (whoſe memory I honour) to be ſpoken ſomewhat in heate of oppoſition and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedly: That the Romiſh <hi>Antichriſt</hi> alone hath more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged the infernall kingdome, then all Iewes, Nero's, Mahomets, Arrians, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Neſtorians, Macedonians, Eutiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and the reſt. Truely I confeſſe (as things now goe)
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8483:35"/>Many a Pope is rather a Bite-ſheepe then a Biſhop (ſo one tearmes him) and much is the woe and wiſterneſſe that <hi>Rome</hi> hath brought vpon Chriſtendome. Many ſoule,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>D. Fulk. in.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. §. 7.</note> falſe, frenzie-full poſitions hath ſhee obtruded to the world on paine of damnation to be beleeued, and ſo great is her Merchandizing that ſhe dare ſet Heauen it ſelfe to ſale.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr. Mountag. appeale. c.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 8</note> But if Turke and Pope together cannot make vp <hi>that</hi> one Antichriſt, and hee may not be both of theſe, nor yet a third out of both theſe. I adde, nor a third beſides theſe. I ſhould rather probably conclude with learned <hi>Zanchius and others more. The Turke is he.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tomo</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>de pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruant. Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. &amp; ib. tract. de fine ſeculi. &amp; tomo.</hi> 8. <hi>Reſponſ. ad Arrianum.</hi>
                     </note> The Turke is he who though he profeſſe himſelfe the Prophet of God, yet exalteth himſelfe againſt all that is called God, and doth moſt blaſphemouſly deny God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acknowledging the Trinitie, nor that holy One, the power of God. The Turke is he who raigneth in that <hi>ſeuen hilled City of Conſtantinople</hi> and ſitteth in the <hi>very</hi> Temple of God. Hieruſalem is his, <hi>and a great part of the world runnes after him.</hi> The <hi>Turke</hi> is he who as <hi>Hanibal</hi> was ſaid of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Scipio</hi> of <hi>Carthage,</hi> is the very ſcourge and plague of Chriſtendome, and Hammer of the world;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cic. Philip.</hi> 4.</note> An enemy implacable, who doth count it his greateſt ſport and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, as one ſaid of <hi>Anthony,</hi> to mangle, murder, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in the bloud of Innocents: yet with that Strumpet in the 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> is content to ſhare the prey, but 'tis with the Deuill. The one ſeekes the <hi>body,</hi> the other the <hi>ſoule.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Good God is it poſſible that the great Princes and Monarches of Chriſtendom can ſo long endure both to heare and ſee this extreme miſery!
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iaques de Lauar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din</hi> Hiſtory <hi>Scanderbeg: lib.</hi> 6.</note> And cannot the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable ſeruitude of their Chriſtian Brethren, their chaines and bonds ſo hydeous and ſhamefull, their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints ſo many, their torments ſo mercileſſe, their bloud ſanctified by Baptiſme leſſe valued then the bloud of beaſt cannot theſe kindle in our hearts the holy fire of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and whet our ſwords againſt that Common e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lucan lib.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note> Cannot this put an end vnto thoſe wofull warres of ours; <hi>Nullos habitura triumphos?</hi> Where one
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8483:36"/>Member wounds another to the hazard of the whole body?
<note place="margin">Revel. 19.2.</note> that ſo wee might auenge the bloud of Gods ſeruants, which hath ſo long time called, cried for reuenge and ſet a bound to Turkes pride and Propagate the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Goſpell of our Sauiour. While now our diſcord is his aduantage, and our warres his opportunitie.</p>
                  <p>There was one
<note n="o" place="margin">Luther. vid vb: Supra.</note> who ſometime,
<note place="margin">So <hi>Fran. Olive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius apud Slei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan. lib.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp; Polidor Virgill lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> ſaid. We might not wage warres againſt the Turkes, and that it was no Chriſtian warrfare: <hi>Aliquid humani paſſus est.</hi> He was a Man and ſo he ſpake. O might I liue to ſee the time when our <hi>Roberts, Godfreies, Baldwins</hi> would ſet foote in ſtirrop againe! <hi>and might I be one of the meaneſt Trumpettors in ſuch an holy expedition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But we muſt Leaue the wound and him that gaue it,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prateol. Haereſ. lib.</hi> 11. §. 38.</note> that we may prouide a plaiſter. The Montaniſt like a timid Chirurgeon doth forſake the cure, and the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Nouatian doth not only paſſe by the wounded man, with the Preiſt and Leuite, without reaching an helping hand; But <hi>ingenioſa &amp; noua crudelitate,</hi> as ſaith S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> wickedly though wittily kills out right. Indeed that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure Puritan <hi>Nouatus</hi> was all for Iudgment, and would not affoard one drop of mercy to thoſe miſerable wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches who in heate of perſecution fell away. No teares, no ſubmiſſion, no ſatisfaction, no poſſible repentance might ſerue the tourne, whereby they might be reconciled, and receiued to the Church againe.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tomo</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>de per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerant. Sanctorum.</hi>
                     </note> Now <hi>Zanchius</hi> is of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the Nouatians were not ſo vnlearned or vnſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the ſcriptures, but that they knew, <hi>At what time ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer a ſinner repenteth of his ſinnes from the bottom of his heart God would forgiue,</hi> but they verily beleeue, that ſuch as committed thoſe grand ſins as to deny their faith, their Sauiour, could neuer haue the grace of true repentance. But we haue promiſes and examples to confute their errors: And the Church did moſt worthily exclude and baniſh them,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lactantius lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 24.</note> who were ſo difficult and inexorable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue others. God commands not impoſſibilities, but ſuch is his goodneſſe, knowing the weakeneſſe and frailty of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:8483:36"/>man. He hath left a doore open whereby man hauing gone amiſſe and returning may enter in,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Homil. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianis Serm.</hi> 15.</note> To thinke God cannot forgiue is againſt his Omnipotency, to thinke he will not forgiue is againſt his Goodneſſe, To doubt of either is againſt his gracious <hi>Come vnto me &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Matth. 11.28. Prouerb. 28.</note> For he that confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſinne ſhall obtaine mercy. And he that taught vs to pray for remiſſion and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe, intended (who dares doubt it) to forgiue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But there are ſinnes, and there are crying ſinnes;
<note place="margin">Acts 18.14. 1 Iohn 5.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſinnes and audacious ſinnes; and ſinnes to death. There are indeed, and to deny our faith is none of thoſe little ones and peccadillios: <hi>But he that loueth friends, lands; life, more then Chriſt is vnworthy of Chriſt.</hi> Math. 14. And how deteſtable ſuch offences are, they may teſtifie whom a preſent vengeance hath ceized on,
<note place="margin">De Lapſis.</note> and who in the middeſt of their eſcape haue felt the powerful reuenging hand of the Almighty. <hi>Cyprian</hi> wil tel you of one ſtriken dumbe, and of another who preſently poſſeſſed with an vncleane ſpirit bit her tounge in pecces, <hi>Poena inde caepit, vnde &amp; crimen.</hi> And diuerſe ſuch like.
<note place="margin">Math. 18.6.7. <hi>Bucan loc.</hi> 17. <hi>Althamer. in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cil. loc. ſcript.</hi> 12 <hi>Vid. Aquin</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. 2<hi>ae. q.</hi> 14. <hi>art.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Zanch. tomo.</hi> 4. <hi>lib.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>cap</hi> 9.</note> In a word tis a <hi>Millſtone</hi> ſinne and ſinne of offence: <hi>and woe to him by whom offence commeth.</hi> But tis not a ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt, though it come neere to that ſinne, nothing neerer when tis not done, <hi>Animo peccandi</hi> willingly, willfully, and maliciouſly. And ſo did <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philact</hi> plead for S. <hi>Peter</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>in Luc.</hi> 22.</note> that he had <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the ſeed, the roote of faith was left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind. And <hi>Gregory</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Apud Zanch. tomo</hi> 7. <hi>de perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerant. Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. In Homil. Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Serm.</hi> 5. <hi>Platina. Carra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nz. &amp;c.</hi> Cyprian.</note> That ſome ſinne of ignorance. So <hi>Paul,</hi> ſome of infirmity, ſo <hi>Peter,</hi> and other ſome out of a deſire and mallicious propenſity to ſinne. To the prince of the Apoſtles I may adioyne that Prince of peace <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> that great one, who fell into ſo great Idolatry. And <hi>Manaſſes</hi> who exceeded all men in abomination of ſinne, yet is he afterward numbred among the friends of God. And <hi>Marcellinus</hi> the Pope, who burnt incenſe, yet at the laſt ſuffered for the faith, and <hi>Caſta</hi> and <hi>Emilius</hi> and a world beſide, who firſt fell, and then repented, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8483:37"/>that they not only obtained pardon of the Church in Earth, but the glorious Crowne of Martyrdome in Heauen.
<note place="margin">In Homil. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian vbi Supra.</note> Yea I know ſome that tell vs how for this very cauſe the Deuill haſted to take <hi>Iudas</hi> out of this life, leaſt knowing that there was a way to turne to Saluation, He might by pennance recouer his fall. I preſſe it not; but yet <hi>Nouatus</hi> muſt heare will he nill he;
<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> That the Church was euer ready to receiue thoſe which returne, her Armes are open, her breaſts naked, and ſhe cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get her Child, and if ſhee could, yet I know who cannot. And therefore though this ſinne of thine be a ſcarlet-ſinne;
<note place="margin">Acts. 8.22.</note> Yet will I not ſay to thee as ſome S <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Simon Magus ſi fortè remittatur. Repent of this thy wickedneſſe, and pray to God that if it be poſſible thou maieſt be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, yea I know thou wilt be forgiuen. But Thou muſt repent and do thy firſt worke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I cannot but approue their ſaying,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Canus. Bucanus, Alſted &amp;c.</hi> 2, Cor. 7.</note> who deriue poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie from <hi>poena</hi> ſorrow within, and ſhame without, but this is not enough, it muſt bee <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> A godly ſorrow which doth cauſe a gracious repentance, feare and griefe doth accompanie the damned, but a Religious ſoule beginnes in ſorrow, walkes on in hope, reſolues on Reformation,
<note place="margin">Herman Coloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis tit. Conuerſ. à peccat.</note> addeth wings to his reſolution, and to finiſh and perfect all labours to doe <hi>The firſt workes,</hi> the workes of Grace. This made one define Repentance to be, an earneſt hearty ſerious ſorrow for our ſinnes, enli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened with the hope of pardon, and accompanied with a firme purpoſe of Amending what hath bin amiſſe. This made Another ſay that to Repent is <hi>iuſtitiam denuò operari.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lactanſius lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. The Booke of Common prayer in princip. <hi>ex</hi> Math. 3.2. <hi>Rhem.</hi> teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in Math. 11. §. 3.</note> Not only to be ſorry for what is done, but ſeriouſly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, purpoſe and liue a better life, and accordingly hath our Church ſomwhere tranſlated Poenitencie into Amendment of life. How euer the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> haue found a knot in a Bullruſh, and diſlike what they can neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend. The common diuiſion of Repentance is into <hi>Contrition, Confeſſion and Satisfaction,</hi> But many thinke it more common then ſafe, and in deteſtation of Auricular
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8483:37"/>confeſſion, or for feare the al-ſufficiency of Chriſts ſatif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction were hereby queſtioned, they cannot brooke, they cannot once endure the name of Confeſſion or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction.</p>
                  <p>And yet the Papiſts make them not <hi>eſſentiall</hi> parts but <hi>Integrall</hi> the <hi>Materialls</hi> or <hi>quaſi materia.</hi> Either as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of or ſomething belonging to repentance: either as parts of poenitency, or
<note n="b" place="margin">ibid &amp; Concil. Florent.</note> acts of the penitent, neceſſary either <hi>vt precepta</hi> or <hi>media</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Concil. Trident. in Catechiſ. ad parachos. inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</note> as things of nature or condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the perfection of Repentance. Many of them haue ſaid no more, and for ought I ſee we ſay as much, for when no ſtone is left vnmoued, and ſicke man like we haue toſſed vs from ſide to ſide, we are ſtill in the ſame place: We admit them all in ſome caſes. As for confeſſion to the Prieſt, our Church approues and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it: indeed as
<note n="e" place="margin">B. Vſſher in anſwer to the Ieſuits challeng pag. 92.</note> 
                     <hi>Medicinall</hi> not <hi>Sacramentall,</hi> and though the Keyes be growne Ruſtie yet are they Rich. But we haue not now to doe with any ſecret ſinne, but with a knowne Capitall offence. And though with the Greeke Church we content our ſelues oft-times with confeſſion to God alone,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Canus parte</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
                        <hi>derelict. poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</hi>
                     </note> yet here together with them we doe admit, approue, vrge a publike <hi>exhomologeſis</hi> open confeſſion and Church diſcipline.</p>
                  <p>As for Satisfaction our intent is not to make Leuell with the Almighty for our ſinnes.
<note place="margin">S. Thom. ex An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelmo. Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factioeſt compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatio Offenſae praeteritae ad ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitatem Iuſtitiae.</note> We know the diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion betweene Mans weakeneſſe, and Gods iuſtice.
<note n="p" place="margin">D. Fulke <hi>ad</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. §. 6. <hi>in Rhem. Teſt. &amp;</hi> againſt Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Fortreſſe. 10. difference.</note> But publike offences may not be ſmothered priuatly, and he that hath giuen ſcandall &amp; offended the Church, muſt to the Church giue Satisfaction. Said I that he muſt? Nay he will, he will willingly. He will cry <hi>ignoſee pater</hi> for his ſin, and <hi>ignoſce frater</hi> for his Example. All his griefe is that he did ſinne, and not that he doth ſuffer, and freely and ingeniouſly he will confeſſe, That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is layed vpon him, whatſoeuer his pennance be either for the humbling of himſelfe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> or for a terror vnto others tis all too little. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> will tell you of a woman ſeduced by <hi>Marke</hi> the Heretike, which did ſpend her
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Concil. Trident. ſeſſ.</hi> 14. <hi>ſub Iulio terti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſeſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Can.</hi> 3.</note>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Booke of common praier.</note>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:8483:38"/>whole time in bewayling her offence, and of others which did <hi>in manifeſto exhomologeſin facore.</hi> publikely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<note place="margin">Ib.</note> and lament their ſinnes and wickedneſſe. <hi>Euſebius</hi> will tell you of an <hi>Hereticall Biſhop,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 28.</note> Natalis</hi> who clad himſelfe in ſackcloth and aſhes falls downe to the feete of the Biſhop,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> and with a world of ſighes, and teares craues pardon. <hi>Socrates</hi> will tell you how <hi>Ecebolius</hi> for renouncing his faith lay along in the Church porch and cryed vnto ſuch as came in. Tread me, Tread me vnder your feete,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>de poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. cap.</hi> 16.</note> for I am the vnſauory Salt. And <hi>Ambroſe</hi> will tell you of Many who did euen plow vp their face with teares, wither their cheeks with weeping, proſtrate themſelues to the feete of the paſſengers, and with their continuall abſtinence and much faſting they made their liuing bodies the very Image of Death. I might adde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all theſe old <hi>Origen</hi> that <hi>Library</hi> of learning and Ocean of woe.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Suida, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſua opera poſt libres</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> But we will paſſe from voluntary ſubmiſſion to <hi>Canonicall ſatisfaction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And here giue me leaue to ſay ſomwhat of the Lawes Eccleſiaſticall and puniſhment inflicted by the Church, that which many ignorantly condemne, and many moſt maliciouſly hew at.
<note place="margin">Lib. de poeniten.</note> 
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> will tell yow that ſuch like offendors as theſe muſt <hi>paſtum &amp; potum pura noſſe.</hi> Bread and water muſt be their diet, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid. <hi>My teares haue beene my meate day and night.</hi> That they muſt pray, and ſigh, and weepe, pray to God, humble themſelues to the Prieſt.
<note place="margin">De mirabil. Sacrae ſcript.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> will tell you that they muſt neuer thinke their pennance enough they muſt alwayes ſorrow, alwayes ory <hi>peccaui,</hi> life and lamentation muſt end together.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De poeniten. lib.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note> S. <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> The more a man throwes himſelfe downe by ſorrow and ſubmiſſion, the more abiect he is in his owne ſight, the more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhall he be in the ſight of God. But this is generall.</p>
                  <p>The Church did appoin certaine formes of pennance according to the quality of the offences,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apud Carranz. cap.</hi> 37. <hi>euiſdem concil.</hi>
                     </note> and for denying the faith <hi>Grandem redeundi difficult atem ſanxit antiquit as</hi> tis a Canon in the <hi>Agathon</hi> Councell about a thouſand
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8483:38"/>yeeres agon. Our forefathers (ſay they) did command and enioyne a bitter pennance to all ſuch as had denyed the faith. Indeed ſome (as 'twas ſaid of <hi>Novatus</hi>) would admit no reconciliation, ſome would receiue <hi>onely once</hi> all ſuch as fell after Baptiſme. The vſuall practiſe was to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne a three yeers pennance, at the leaſt, to ſuch as did in time of perſecution and againſt their wil deny: ſome had their puniſhment prolonged euen vnto 8. or 9 yeeres or more; and ſome were put of <hi>ad magnum diem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Carranz. in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Ancyran. Can.</hi> 6. <hi>Ibid. Can.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note> Euen till the hower of death or day of Iudgement. And if he were a Prieſt that fell. He loſt his orders, nor might he euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer his former ſtrate, but by enduringe the brunt of a ſecond perſecution. And laſt of all,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib. Eccleſ. Hiſt.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>tomo</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 10. <hi>Byſh. Alloy in Miſcellan names 4 ſorts. ex Con. Nicen. Moſes &amp; Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp;c. inter operae Cyprian. tomo.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 26</note> if any were reſtored either of the Laiety or otherwiſe, it muſt be done by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands and confirmation of the Biſhop: And this <hi>Euſebius</hi> calls the ancient cuſtome, and <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that to doe otherwiſe were to ruinate and not reſtore. Now during the time of theſe long appointed pennance, Some were <hi>Audi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntes,</hi> and might only ſtay the Sermon: other were <hi>Orantes</hi> and might be preſent at prayers, but muſt depart when the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> was to be adminiſtred. To admit them to the Communion, was to giue that which is holy to dogs, ſome ſome,
<note place="margin">De Lapſis. Exam. Concil. Triden. parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tis.</note> and to preſſe to the Altar was <hi>Domini corpus invadere.</hi> So <hi>Cyprian,</hi> yet all this while there were Relaxations, moderations, mitigations, or as the <hi>new word</hi> (after <hi>Chemnitius</hi>) hath it, <hi>indulgency</hi> from that rigor and ſeueritie, &amp; there was a peculiar reſerued power in the <hi>R.R.</hi> By ſhop
<note n="o" place="margin">
                        <hi>Concil. Ancyran Can.</hi> 2 <hi>&amp;.</hi> 5. <hi>F. Th. Chauius. de contrit.</hi>
                     </note> He might either lengthen or ſhorten the time as he ſaw cauſe. For as one ſaith out of <hi>Hierom. Apud deum non tantum valet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tenſura temporis quàm doloris.</hi> God regardeth not the length of the pennance, but the Contrition of the party; not how long, but how heartily we humble our ſelues.</p>
                  <p>This was the Diſcipline of the primatiue Church, this was the remedy they did prouide againſt thoſe crimſon.
<note place="margin">2. <hi>in Verrem.</hi>
                     </note> Capitall offences, that as the Orator ſaid, they might <hi>eur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> not couer the wound, and labour to profit, rather then to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:8483:39"/>pleaſe the patient.
<note place="margin">So <hi>Clerus Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus ad Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum inter eius opera tomo</hi> 1. <hi>ep.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> That neither the wicked might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by their Facility, nor religious mindes diſhear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened by their Cruelty: and yet of the twaine, it was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with <hi>Domitius</hi> to be thought ſeuere in puniſhing, then diſſolute in praetermitting, paſſing by the wickedneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Thus were ſome ſtrengthened in the faith, and armed againſt lapſes, others were made to ſee the greatnes of the ſin, and terrified againſt relapſes. All were framed, ordered, tuned, to a moſt wiſhed happy harmony, in the Church of God.</p>
                  <p>Yet Maſter <hi>Cartwright,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Reply pag.</hi> 41.</note> that diſturber of Sions peace,</hi> will cry out againſt the Churches ſeuerity, extreme, exceſſiue ſeuerity: and though he ſomewhere tell vs, That Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Adulterers, and Inceſtuous perſons muſt dye the death;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 36.</note> The Magiſtrate cannot ſaue them, (ſuch is this mild <hi>Moſes</hi> mercy toward thoſe.) yet here <hi>pardon, pardon, pardon.</hi> And leſt he might ſeeme any way to fauour the proceedings of the Roman Church, though when ſhee was yonger by 14. hundred yeeres, then now ſhe is; Hee tels yee,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jbid. pag.</hi> 149.</note> that if offendors be not meete to receiue the holy Sacrament of the Supper, they are not meete to heare the Word of God, they are not meete to be partakers of the prayers of the Church, and if they be for one, they are alſo for the other.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Caluin. Jnſtitut. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. § 6. <hi>Jbid. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 12. § 8.</note> But this is he who thinkes it more ſafe for vs to conforme our indifferent Ceremonies to the Turkes, which are a farre off, than to the Papiſts, which are ſo neere. Indeed <hi>his Maſter tels vs,</hi> that the Church did vſe too much rigour. And would know, <hi>ſi Deus tam, benignus eſt, vt quid Sacerdos eius austerus vult videri?</hi> God (ſaith he) is mercifull and gracious, why ſhould his Prieſt be ſo auſtere and rigorous?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jbid. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. § 10. <hi>Art.</hi> 33.</note> And yet <hi>Caluin</hi> here in our caſe will haue the ſinner yeeld ſufficient teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his ſorrow, that the ſcandall which the offender hath giuen, may be obliterated and taken away. And it muſt be <hi>palam in templo,</hi> and ſo doth our Church teach The offendor muſt be openly reconciled by pennance.</p>
                  <p>Indeed we might be as vnreaſonably plauſible as of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:8483:39"/>ther ſome are, and with thoſe <hi>Heſterni,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cyprian tomo</hi> 1. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 10. Pro. 22.28. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 40. <hi>lib.</hi> 6 <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> cals <hi>Praxeas,</hi> we might remoue the ancient bounds which our Fathers haue ſet. We might be as vnhappily, vndiſcreetly, mercifull as <hi>Foeliciſsimus</hi> in <hi>Cyprian,</hi> or another, if it be true in <hi>Socrates;</hi> we might after a welcome home, admit them to the Church and Sacraments,
<note place="margin">Cyprian de lapſis</note> but it would proue a worſe perſecution then the firſt; and we ſhould call them <hi>A medela vulneris,</hi> it were the way to kill out-right,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jdem tomo</hi> 1. <hi>epiſt</hi> 10. <hi>Serm. de Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto Abbate.</hi>
                     </note> and not to cure the diſeaſe. <hi>Quae nimis properè minus proſperè.</hi> The words are <hi>Bernards,</hi> but it is a prouerbe of our own: <hi>More haſt than good ſpeed.</hi> This made ſome holy men of old pray; that thoſe which had fallen, might know and acknowledge the greatneſſe of their fall, that ſo they might learne <hi>non momentaneam ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> praepraperam deſider are medicinam.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Clerus Romanus ad Cyprianum inter eius opera, tomo</hi> 1. <hi>epiſt</hi> 31.</note> That they might with all fearefull humbleneſſe <hi>expect,</hi> and not audaciouſly <hi>preſume</hi> a pardon. But to ſoder thoſe rents, to daube the breach with vntempered morter, to incarnate on the ſplintred bones, to cry peace, peace, in a preſent perill, and the greateſt danger; what is this elſe, but to precipitate and plunge a poore diſtreſſed ſoule into a more perplexed caſe and deſperate diſeaſe? It is a terrible lenitie, as ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Terribilis leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, blanda per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicies, ſtulta mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordia. Bern ſerm.</hi> 42. <hi>ſuper Cantica.</hi>
                     </note> a courteous miſchiefe, as S. <hi>Cyprian;</hi> a fooliſh pitty, as S. <hi>Bernard: Miſericor diam hanc ego nolo:</hi> God keepe all poore ſinne-ſicke ſoules from ſuch Phyſitians. <hi>Let the righteous ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſmite me friendly, and reproue me; but let not their precious balmes breake my head.</hi> Let me know my dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and whence I am fallen, that I may repent, and doe the firſt workes.</p>
                  <p>If much be remitted of the ancient ſeuerity, as we ſee there is, and the puniſhment be much leſſe then thoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue times did vſually inflict: it is not becauſe the ſin is now leſſe, or the compaſſion of the faithfull greater; for that ancient diſcipline is to be wiſhed for againe,
<note place="margin">Church-booke <hi>ante Comminat. Tertul. de p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. cap.</hi> 1.</note> but theſe delicate times will not ſuffer it. And the Church is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to condiſcend to the weakeneſſe of her children. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men are become <hi>pudoris magis memores quàm ſalutis.</hi>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:8483:40"/>They will rather hazard the loſſe of heauen, than endure diſgr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> account it) on the earth.</p>
                  <p>And this is the very cauſe why many, and as I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, many hundreds, are Muſſelmans in Turkie, and Chriſtians at home; doffing their religion, as they doe their clothes, and keeping a conſcience for euery Harbor wheere they ſhall put in. And thoſe Apoſtates and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Renegadoes, thinke they haue diſcharged their Conſcience wondrous well, if they can Returne, and (the fact vnknowne) make profeſſion of their firſt faith. Theſe men are cowards, and flexible before the fall; careleſſe and obſtinate after it: but what good will it doe them, ſaith <hi>Lactantius,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Bern. in Pſal. Qui habitat. ſerm.</hi> 11. <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 24.</note> non habere conſcium, &amp; habere conſcientiam?</hi> to haue no witneſſe without, and one within? to hide their ſinnes from men, and to appeare as they are to the righteous Iudge, from whoſe eyes nothing is hid, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſecret? to be baptiſed with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and yet liue in the gall of bitterneſſe, and bond of iniquity? Theſe are thoſe curſed wretches to whom <hi>proprius interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſatis non fuit:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cyprian de lapſis.</note> who will not periſh alone, but both by their example, and their exhortation, draw others into the ſame pit of perdition alſo; who doe adde ſinne to ſin, and multiply and aggrauate their offences, by hiding, denying, excuſing, tranſlating ſinne. So that they may be Men here, they care not to be diuels afterward. If any ſuch be here, who hath receiued the Marke of the Beaſt, and liues vnknowne; yet for Gods ſake, for his owne ſake, for that ſweet Name by which he is named the Name of Chriſt: by the hope of heauen, by the feare of hell; by his friends on earth,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gregory Nyſſen.</hi> in the end of his Homil of Repentance. <hi>Si vis curam, agnoſce languorem. P. Chryſolog. ſerm.</hi> 30.</note> and the holy Angels in heauen, who ioy at the conuerſion of a ſinner, by whatſoeuer is deereſt vnto him, and nothing ſhould be deerer than his ſoule. I ſhall, I doe beſeech ſuch a one to be mercifull to his owne life. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c. Get thee to ſome learned Prieſt, open thy griefe to the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian of thy ſoule: He will, compaſſionate thy caſe with a fatherly affection: ſhew vnto him without bluſhing, thoſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8483:40"/>ſecret ſores of thine: and he will (or be he branded for euer with the ignominy of Irregularity) he will ſaue thy credit, and ſalue thy wound. Credit? alas, alas, what's Credit if the ſoule muſt periſh? or what's Reputation, which cannot compaſſe one drop of water to coole a fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming tongue?</p>
                  <p>And you whom God ſuffered to fall, and yet of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercy vouchſafed graciouſly to bring home, not onely to your country and kindred, but to the profeſſion of your firſt faith, and to the Church and Sacraments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Let me ſay to you (but in a better houre) as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time <hi>Ioſuah</hi> to <hi>Achan:</hi> Giue glory to God, ſing praiſes to him who hath deliuered your ſoule from the nethermoſt hell: Magnifie him for his vnſpeakeable goodneſſe and mercy towards you: labour not either to couer, or leſſen your offence.</p>
                  <p>When I thinke vpon your Turkiſh attire, that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of Apoſtacie, and witneſſe of your wofull fall; I doe remember <hi>Adam</hi> and his figge-leaue breeches; they could neither conceale his ſhame, nor couer his naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I doe thinke vpon <hi>Dauid</hi> clad in <hi>Sauls</hi> armour,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.</note> and his helmet of braſſe. I cannot goe with theſe, ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid:</hi> How could you hope in this vnſanctified habit to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine heauen? how could you, clad in this vnchriſtian weede; how could you but with horror and aſtoniſhment thinke on the white robe of the innocent Martyrs which you had loſt?
<note place="margin">Reuel. 6.11.</note> How could you goe in theſe rewards of iniquity, and guerdons of apoſtacie? and with what face could you behold your ſelfe and others?</p>
                  <p>I doe aſſure my ſelfe, the torments you endured, were grieuous, &amp; the hope for your deliuery, was little or none: but <hi>Seneca</hi> puts it downe for an Axiome; that a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be much grieued, and long together; and that the paines will be either ſufferable, or ſhort:
<note place="margin">Ep. 97. <hi>Philip. decimn.</hi>
                     </note> if it be not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſo. Yet what ſaith <hi>Cicero</hi> of <hi>Trebonius</hi> miſerably ſlaine by <hi>Dolebella? Sickneſſe doth oft times puniſh many of vs here, as much and much more, than ſtripes could torment
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:8483:41"/>you there.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertul.</hi> 76.</note> Howeuer the longeſt day hath a night, and the torments and tormentors cannot laſt for euer: but <hi>montes vruntur &amp; durant. Aetna</hi> and <hi>Veſuuius</hi> burne and continue. We ſhould thinke vpon the paines of hell which laſt for euer.</p>
                  <p>I know you were young; ſo was <hi>Daniel</hi> and the three Children:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 40. <hi>Gr.</hi> 41. <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Fox. Zuinger.</hi>
                     </note> ſo were <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> the Confeſſor, and <hi>Ponticus</hi> the Martyr: adde (if you pleaſe) our Engliſh Mekins, who all at fifteene yeeres of age endured manfully whatſoeuer the furie of the perſecutors pleaſed to inflict vpon them. I might adioyne to theſe ſome of ten yeeres old, and <hi>Vitus</hi> of ſeuen. And (though we call them the weaker ſexe) yet hath the Church her Women-Martyrs, not a few, who haue endured as couragiouſly as euer any then did.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ambroſ. de vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginib. lib.</hi> 1.</note> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe S. <hi>Agnes</hi> at 12. yeeres old; <hi>Cecilia, Agatha,</hi> &amp; a world beſides.</p>
                  <p>In a word, youth and torments, and what euer elſe may be alleadged, doe ſomewhat leſſen and extenuate the ſinne, but they cannot cleare the conſcience. Wee are bound without fainting to reſiſt vnto the death.</p>
                  <p>I would be loath to breake a bruiſed reede, or adde af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction to affliction. Let not what is ſaid or done, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage any of you to reioyce in your neighbours fall, nor triumph in his miſery. Farre be all vnchriſtian vpbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, reproches, twittings, from your Chriſtian hearts; but as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Oneſimus; Receiue him as a beloued bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for euer, and doe it with the ſpirit of meekeneſſe, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your ſelues,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.1. <hi>Ille bodie ego eras,</hi> ſo <hi>ille a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Bern. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrect. Domin. ſerm.</hi> 2.</note> leſt you alſo be tempted.</hi> God forbid that any of you ſhould grieue his ſoule, for whoſe returne the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels doe reioyce in heauen. Prophets, Patriarkes, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Angels, haue fallen, and who is he that is aſſured of his ſtrength? or who can ſay he ſhall ſtand faſt for euer? Though you trafficke not for Turkie, yet may you bee Apoſtata's at home,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Tim. 5.8.</note> denying in deeds, and worſe than In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels.</p>
                  <p>But you that goe downe to the ſea in ſhippes, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie your buſineſſe in great waters (for the ſtate of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8483:41"/>world cannot ſtand without buying and ſelling, traffique and tranſportation) what ſhall I ſay of you? <hi>Pittacus</hi> reckons you neither amongſt the dead, nor the liuing. The graue is alway open before your face, and but the thickneſſe of an inch or twaine that keepes you from it: One breath, flaw, guſt, may end your voyage. But if <hi>Paul</hi> ſcape drowning, yet he ſees a Viper on the ſhore, and if all dangers of the ſea quit you, yet a miſchiefe from the land may ouertake you. That <hi>African</hi> monſter, to which ſo many poore ſoules haue been made a prey; The Turke, (which God forbid) may bring you vnder his Lee.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 21.18.</note> And as our Sauiour ſaid of <hi>Peter,</hi> you ſhall ſtretch forth your hands, and he ſhall gird you, and leade you whither you would not. If ſuch a calamity ſhould euer befall any of you, yet remember your firſt loue, the God of loue, your bleſſed Sauiour: <hi>fight a good fight,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.</note> keeping faith and a good conſcience.</hi> So ſhall Chriſt heare when you call, and ſhall deliuer you in the needfull time of trouble: He ſhall bring you backe vnto your home in ſafety; and as you haue confeſſed him before men, ſo ſhall he confeſſe you before his father which is in heauen.</p>
                  <p>The firſt workes come now in the laſt place to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of; this is one of the liſſoms or twiſts of that coard which will hardly be broken.
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.12.</note> 
                     <hi>Remember, repent, and doe the firſt workes.</hi> Workes muſt be one, or it will neuer hold,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Serm.</hi> 16. <hi>in Cantica.</hi>
                     </note> but adde them, and you ſhall make S. <hi>Bernards</hi> rope; ſtrong enough to draw ſoules out of the diuels Gaole. I ſhould here tell this poore penitent, what one tels the Citizens of <hi>Luca.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. Martyr.</note> It behoueth him to make good what he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly and faintingly denyed. He muſt caſt off his barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous barbarian habit, and putting on a Chriſtian reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; he muſt boldly confeſſe his Sauiour <hi>in the ſame place,</hi> where he did firſt deny him; or becauſe <hi>Durus eſt hic ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o,</hi> as they ſay in the 6. of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> this is an hard ſaying: and it is indeed, and requires a ſpeciall fortitude and moſt heauenly reſolution: and <hi>non omnes capiunt;</hi> it muſt be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them from aboue: yet in the whole courſe of his life,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8483:42"/>let his repentance be made manifeſt, and let him ingraue in his heart thoſe words of the Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.39.</note> 
                     <hi>Nor death, nor life, nor Augels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth,</hi> nor Turke nor Atheiſt, <hi>nor any other Creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate him from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And I ſhould ſay, ſomewhat of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> of them, and to them; for I feare me they haue a populous poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6. Iam. 2.17.</note> euen in our owne land. Workes without faith are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable; and faith without workes is dead: nor will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery worke ſerue, but there muſt be
<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>feruency</hi> in prayer,
<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 9.7.</note> 
                     <hi>cheerefulneſſe</hi> in giuing; a
<note n="c" place="margin">Titus 3.1.</note> 
                     <hi>promptneſſe,</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Coloſ. 1.10.</note> 
                     <hi>fruitfulneſſe,</hi> and an
<note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. vlc.</note> 
                     <hi>abounding</hi> in euery good worke:
<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.26.</note> ſo run, ſo fight, <hi>ſpero meliora</hi> muſt be your Motto. Doe what you can, yet know you can neuer doe enough. Lippe-religion doth but ſet an edge vpon GODS anger, and make man the more in excuſable;
<note place="margin">Iames 1.22.</note> and therefore ſee that yee be Doers of the Word,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.25.</note> and not Hearers onely, deceiuing your ſelues. And ſo heare, ſo doe, as men that ſtriue for the maſtery: they doe it, as the Apoſtle ſaith, to obtaine a corruptible Crowne; and the height of their hopes is but <hi>vnius horae hila<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is inſania:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.37. <hi>In Homil. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian. ſerm.</hi> 16.</note> I went by, and loe they were gone; but you ſhall eſcape that ſtrange darke, durable fire of hell, where the worme dyeth not; and ſhall be receiued into your maſters ioy; into the bleſſed fellowſhip of Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, into the glorious liberty of other the ſonnes of God: as children, heires, co-heires with Chriſt, you ſhall bee glorified with him. To whom be aſcribed all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour glory, power and praiſe for euer,</p>
                  <trailer>AMEN.
<hi>FINIS.</hi>
                  </trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8483:42"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
